<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine vppon the Epistle to the Philippians wherein is set out the necessitie and profite of affliction vnto the faithfull, the benefite of God his word, the fruits, of vnitie and humilitie, free iustification by faith in Iesus Christ without our owne merites, the assurance, ioy, and contented mindes of the godlie, and their perseueraunce in godlinesse vnto the end. With many other comfortable and profitable pointes of religion. Translated out of Latine by W.B.</title>
            <title>Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4402</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843080</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843080</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7789</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7789)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 918:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine vppon the Epistle to the Philippians wherein is set out the necessitie and profite of affliction vnto the faithfull, the benefite of God his word, the fruits, of vnitie and humilitie, free iustification by faith in Iesus Christ without our owne merites, the assurance, ioy, and contented mindes of the godlie, and their perseueraunce in godlinesse vnto the end. With many other comfortable and profitable pointes of religion. Translated out of Latine by W.B.</title>
                  <title>Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Becket, William, fl. 1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By John Windet] for Nicolas Lyng, and are to be sold at the west dore of S. Paules Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1584.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.B. = William Becket.</note>
                  <note>A translation of part of: Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Page number 95 is inverted.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A commentarie of I. Caluine, vpon the Philippians.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Philippians --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Commentarie</hi> of M. Iohn Caluine vppon the Epiſtle to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians, wherein is ſet out the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie and profite of affliction vnto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the benefite of God his word, the fruits, of vnitie and humilitie, free iuſtification by faith in Ieſus Chriſt without our owne merites, the aſſurance, ioy, and contented mindes of the godlie, and their perſeueraunce in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe vnto the end. With many other comfortable and profitable pointes of Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Latine by W. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at London for Nicolas Lyng, and are to be ſold at the Weſt dore of S. Paules Church. <hi>Anno.</hi> 1584.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right honourable, Sir Frances <hi>VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingham, Knight, chiefe ſecretary vnto hir Maieſty, chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> of the order, and one of hir Maieſties moſte honorable priuie counſell, <hi>William Becket</hi> wiſheth <hi>encreaſe of honor, and all heauenly happines.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iomedes</hi> a prince of the Grecians <hi>(Right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable)</hi> as <hi>Homer</hi> in his Iliades recordeth, embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened by <hi>Pallas,</hi> feared no whit at all the force of the <hi>Troianes,</hi> nor the ſtrength &amp; multitude of their confederates: but valiantly for his Countries ſafety, hazarded his life amids his enimies. And my ſelfe hoping of your honors fauourable protection, not regarding the curious carping of a great ſort in theſe daies: for the benefite of many haue yeelded my ſelfe to be cenſured of all. For as to encourage &amp; animate a Captaine there can be none fitter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Pallas,</hi> to whom the ancient writers haue aſcribed both wiſdome in giuing counſel, &amp; couragiouſnes in fight: ſo for your great loue of godlines, &amp; ſingular zeale in furthering of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is none more fit than your honor to whom this godly commentary of maiſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> diſcourſing of many excellent points of our religion, might be preſented. For here is ſet out the condition of the godly, how the Lord in this life hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth them by afflictions, and after receiueth them to eternall glory. Here is ſet out their aſſurance of Gods fauour, their ioy in greateſt dangers, and their contented minds in all estates. Here is ſet out the benefite that commeth by preaching of the goſpell, and the malice, practiſes, and confuſion of falſe teachers. Here is ſet out the fruite of humility, the neceſſity of vnity and agrement among the faithfull, free iustification by Ieſus Chriſt, the heauenly conuerſation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and how they muſt continue ſtedfaſt in godlines vnto the ende. And although I offer theſe being another mans laboures, vnder my owne name: yet neither enuiouſly to derogate any thing from the due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of ſo worthy a perſon (as <hi>Homeromaſtix</hi> did) nor pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly by another mans trauels to ſeeke my own praiſe as that vaine-glorious Poet, who preſented <hi>Virgils</hi> verſes, as if they had beene his owne, vnto <hi>Auguſtus</hi> the Emperor. But conſidering that
<pb facs="tcp:7789:3"/> a good thing the more common it is, the more comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dable &amp; better it is (eſpecially being requested therevnto) for the comfort and profit of all true Engliſh christians, I haue made that common to all, which afore was priuate, but to a fewe. We ſay in our common prouerbe that good wine neede no Iuie buſh, &amp; a naked truth barely vttered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any filed phraſes of fine eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is of it ſelf ſufficiently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. And this worke (how ſimplie ſoeuer I haue tranſlated it, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding faithfully) being written by the holy Apostle inſpired with Gods ſpirit, &amp; expounded by ſo notable a father of the Church, cannot but carry with it amongſt all good men ſufficient credite. I haue therefore preſumed, not only to preſent it vnto your honorable view, but alſo vnder your name, as a ſufficient ſhielde againſt al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries to publiſh it vnto al. Moſt humbly beſeeching your honor with your accustomed fauour to accept theſe first fruites of my trauels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; not to meaſure the ſimplenes of the gift with the worthines of your owne perſon: but rather to reſpect the good will and willing deſire I had in moſt humble maner by al dutie poſſible to gratifie your honor. So ſhall I not only be encouraged, to the vttermoſt of my ſimple ſkill to employ my ſelfe to the profit of others: but alſo as afore by generall dutie, ſo now by particular benefite I ſhall be bound to pray for the preſeruation of your honor in health, and increaſe of dignitie, godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, vertue, and all heauenly happines. The Almighty mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his graces vpon you, and grant you as many proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous yeares, as vertuous &amp; godly properties (and both infinite) that here you may liue long to his glory, &amp; hereafter liue for euer, to your owne euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting comfort.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all humble dutie, WILLLIAM BECKET.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7789:3"/>
            <head>THE ARGVMENT OF the epiſtle of S, Paule written <hi>vnto the Philippians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is manifeſt, that <hi>Philippos</hi> is a citie of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> ſituate in the borders of <hi>Thracia:</hi> in whoſe fieldes <hi>Pompeius</hi> was vanquiſhed by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp; afterward <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi> ouercome by <hi>Antonius</hi> and <hi>Octauius.</hi> Thus the diſſention of the Romanes, by two notable battells, made the place famous. When <hi>Paule</hi> by a viſion was come into <hi>Macedonia,</hi> he layd the foundation of the Church firſt in that citie, as <hi>Luke</hi> recordeth in the 16. of the Acts, and 12. verſe: the which, how it did not onely continue conſtantly in the faith, but alſo by continuance of time, numbers of men, and going forward in vertue, it was encreaſed, this epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth teſtifie. Furthermore this was the cauſe, why <hi>Paule</hi> did write vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> when they by <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> their Paſtor, had ſent vnto him thoſe thinges that were needefull for him in bonds, to preſerue life, and for other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary charges: it is no doubt but <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> as well opened vnto him the eſtate of the Church, as was a perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſupply thoſe things, whereof they were to be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. For it appeareth that they were tempted of falſe prophets, which at that time wandered all abroad to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſound doctrine: but becauſe they perſiſted in the truth, <hi>Paule</hi> commendeth their conſtancie, yet being mindfull of the frailtie that is in men, and admoniſhed perhaps by <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus,</hi> that they were ſpeedily to be confirmed: leſt they ſhould againe fall, he ioyneth ſuch admonitions, as he knew
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7789:4"/> were conuenient for them. And firſt of all hauing teſtified the kinde affection of his mind toward them, whereby he might procure credite: he ſpeaketh of him ſelfe, and of his owne bondes, that they ſhould not faint, becauſe they ſawe him taken priſoner, and in daunger of his life. Therefore he ſheweth that it is ſo far of, that thereby the glorie of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſhould be diminiſhed, that it was rather an argument to confirme it: and together with his owne example, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth them to be readye to endure all things: at length with an exhortation vnto vnitie and patience, he conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the firſt chapter. But becauſe ambition is for the moſt part a continuall mother of diſſention, whereof it commeth to paſſe, that there is a doore open to newe and ſtrange do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: in the beginning of the ſecond chapter, he earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeecheth them, that they would preferre nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore humilitie and modeſtie: and vnto that he vſeth many arguments. And that he might the better keepe them in their dutie, he promiſeth that he will ſend <hi>Timotheus</hi> vnto them ſhortly: yea he putteth them alſo in hope of his owne comming: afterward he excuſeth the tarying of <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> In the third chapter, he inueigheth againſt the falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and refuteth as well their vaine boaſtings, as the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of circumciſion, which they vrged: againſt all their inuentions, he oppoſeth onely Chriſt: againſt their arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, he oppoſeth as well his owne former life, as his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe, wherein did ſhine the image of Chriſtian god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines. And this he aduertiſeth vs to be the ſcope of our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, (whether thorough out all our life we muſt ſtriue to come) to communicate with Chriſt in his death, and in his reſurrection: and he proueth it by his owne example. The fourth chapter he beginneth with particular admonitions, and forthwith deſcendeth into generall. And he concludeth the epiſtle with a teſtimonie of his thankefulnes toward the <hi>Philippians,</hi> leſt they ſhould thinke that ill beſtowed, which they had employed to the releeuing of his neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:7789:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A COMMENTARIE OF</hi> IOHN CALVINE VPON THE EPISTLE OF PAVLE vnto the Philippians.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1</hi>
                        </bibl> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aule and Timotheus, ſeruants of Ieſus Christ, to all the Sainctes in Christ Ieſus, which are at Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippos, with Biſhops and Deacons.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2</hi>
                        </bibl> Grace be with you, and peace from God our father, and from our Lord Ieſus Christ.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>3</hi>
                        </bibl> I thanke my God in all remembrance of you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>4</hi>
                        </bibl> Alwaies in all my prayers, praying for you all with ioy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>5</hi>
                        </bibl> For your fellowſhip in the Goſpell, from the first day vntill nowe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>6</hi>
                        </bibl> Being thus perſwaded that he that hath begunne a good worke in you, will finiſh it vnto the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <head>Cap. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aule, &amp;c.</hi> Séeing that it was <hi>Paule</hi> his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to write his title, to procure more cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite vnto him ſelfe and his miniſterie: he née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no farther words of commendation vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> who had tried him to be the true Apoſtle of Chriſt, and did yet acknowledge it without controuerſie: for conſtantly and in an euen courſe they had gone forward in the calling of God. <hi>Biſhops.</hi> He nameth the Paſtors ſeuerally for honors ſake. Moreouer, hereof we may gather, that the name of a Biſhop is common to all the miniſters of the word, ſince that he doth attribute mo Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops vnto one Church. A Biſhop and a Paſtor therefore ſignifie one thing. And this place among the reſt is one, which <hi>Hierom</hi> doth cite to proue the ſame thing, in his epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Euagrius,</hi> and in his expoſition vpon the epiſtle to <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Afterward it grewe to a cuſtome, that whome the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7789:5"/> in their ſeuerall Churches had ſet ouer their congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he alone ſhould be called a Biſhop, notwithſtanding that procéeded from the cuſtome of men, and dependeth not vpon the authoritie of the Scripture. Yet I confeſſe, as the wittes and manners of men are nowe, there can no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtand among the miniſters of the worde, except one be ſette ouer the reſt. I ſpeake of the ſeuerall bodies of the Church, not of whole prouinces, much leſſe of the whole world: notwithſtanding although we muſt not contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout wordes, yet it were farre better, in ſpeaking to follow the Holie Ghoſt, being the Author of tongues, than to change the formes of ſpeaking ſet downe by him, for worſe. For of the corrupt ſignification of the worde, this euill haue enſued: that, as though all Elders were not fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es called to the ſame office, one vnder the colour of this newe name, haue challenged vnto him ſelfe a dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the reſt. <hi>Deacons.</hi> This name may be taken two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of waies, either for the collectors and prouiders for the poore, or for the Elders that were appointed Cenſors of their manners: but becauſe it is more vſed by <hi>Paule</hi> in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſence, I rather vnderſtande houſholders, who were chiefe in receiuing and diſtributing of the almes.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 <hi>Grace be with you and peace.</hi>
                  </hi> Nothing is more to be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for, than that God ſhould be fauourable vnto vs, which is ſignified by <hi>Grace:</hi> then that from him proſperitie, and good ſucceſſe in all things ſhould procéede, which is ſignified vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the word <hi>Peace.</hi> For howbeit all things ſéeme to pleaſe vs: if God be angry, euen the very bleſſing is turned into a curſe. Therefore the good will of God, is the onely foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our happines, whereby it commeth to paſſe, that we enioy true and perfect proſperitie: and euen by aduerſitie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, our ſaluation groweth forward. Moreouer, whereas he praieth Peace from God, we vnderſtand that whatſoeuer goodnes happen vnto vs, it is the fruite of God his liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Neither muſt we omit, that he alſo praieth for theſe good things, from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. For worthily is this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7789:5"/> honor giuen vnto him, who is not onely the miniſter and diſpoſer of his fathers bountie toward vs, but alſo worketh all things iointly together with him. Yet the Apoſtle would note properly, that all the benefits of God doe come vnto vs thorough him. There are ſome that by the word Peace, had rather vnderſtand the peace of conſcience, in the which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, I deny not, but it is ſometimes vſed. But ſince it is certaine, that the Apoſtle would here knit vp the ſumme of all good things, the former interpretation which is giuen by <hi>Bucere,</hi> is more conuenient. Therefore willing to wiſhe the ſumme of all happines vnto the godly, he commeth vnto the fountaine it ſelfe, namely vnto the grace of God: which alone doth not onely bring vs eternall bleſſednes, but is the cauſe of all good things in this life.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 <hi>I thanke God.</hi>
                  </hi> He beginneth with a gratulation for two cauſes, that by this reaſon he might proue his loue to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> and by praiſing thoſe thinges that are paſt, might exhort them hereafter to goe forward. The other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his loue, he ſetteth downe to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carefulnes, which he expreſſed in his praiers. Here we muſt note, that as oft as he maketh mention of ioyfull things, forthwith he burſteth forth into a thankeſgiuing, which cuſtome ſhould alſo be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar vnto vs. It is alſo to be noted for what cauſe he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thanks vnto God, namely for the fellowſhip of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> in the Goſpel of Chriſt: for thereof followeth that it muſt be acknowledged to haue bene receiued of the grace of God. Where he ſaith, <hi>In al remembrance of you,</hi> that ſignifie, as oft as I remember you. <hi>Alwaies in all my praiers.</hi> Ioyne the words thus, Praying alwaies for you all in all my praiers. For as before he ſayd the remembrance of them was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of his ioy: ſo now he addeth, that they are in his mind when he praieth. After he addeth, that he maketh his prayer for them with ioy. Ioy is referred to the time paſt, prayer to the time future: for he did reioyce in their happy beginnings, but wiſhed their perfection. So it behoueth vs alwaies to reioice for the benefits of God, which we haue receiued, that we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7789:6"/> might remember to deſire of him thoſe things which as yet we want. <hi>5 <hi>For your fellowſhip.</hi>
                  </hi> Nowe omitting the other clauſe, he ſheweth what his ioy is: namely, becauſe they were come into the fellowſhip of the Goſpel, that is, they were made partakers of the Goſpell, which is wel knowen to be done by faith: for the goſpel doth nothing pertaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that we ſhould enioy it, vntill it be receiued of vs by faith: although the name of fellowſhip may be referred vnto the common ſocietie of the ſainctes: as if he ſhould ſay, they were gathered vnto al the ſonnes of God, into the faith of the Goſpel. Further when he ſaith, <hi>from the firſt day,</hi> he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth their readines, becauſe they ſhewed them ſelues eaſie to be taught, ſo ſoone as the doctrine was propounded vnto them: this word <hi>vntill now,</hi> doth note their perſeuerance. We know what a rare vertue it is, by and by to follow God when he calleth, &amp; conſtantly to go forward vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende. For many men are ſlow, &amp; hard to obey, &amp; more do faint by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; inconſtancie. <hi>6 <hi>Being thus perſwaded.</hi>
                  </hi> To the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ioy, he addeth the truſt he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of their life afterward: but ſome wil ſay: how dare men be ſo bold in ſuch weakenes of nature, among ſo many hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, ſlidings &amp; downefals, as to promiſe vnto them ſelues any thing touching to morrow? Truly <hi>Paule</hi> did not gather this truſt from the conſtancie &amp; vertue of men, but onely of this, that God had declared his loue toward the <hi>Philippians.</hi> And this is altogether the true acknowledging of God his benefits, when of them we conceiue a matter to hope wel for the time afterward: for ſince they are teſtimonies both of his bountie, &amp; of his fatherly good will toward vs, what ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude were it, from thence to receiue no confirmation of hope, &amp; of his good wil toward vs? Adde hereunto that God is not like men, who can be weary with doing good, or drawn dry, that he can not. Therefore let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithful exerciſe them ſelues in continuall meditation of God his benefits, that they may cheriſh &amp; confirme the hope of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to come: &amp; alwaies let them repeate this ſyllogiſme with them ſelues. God neuer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7789:6"/> forſaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> works of his owne hands which he hath begun, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet witneſſeth. We are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of his hands, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he wil finiſh that he hath begun in vs. <hi>Iſai. 64.8.</hi> When I ſay we are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of his hands, I do not take it onely of his creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by his vocation wherby we are adopted to be his ſons. For this is vnto vs a ſigne of our electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord by his ſpirit hath effectually called vs vnto him ſelf. But here a queſtion is aſked, whether any man can be certaine of an other mans ſaluation? For <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh not here of him ſelf, but of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Philippians,</hi> I anſwere, that euery man haue a farre other certaintye of his owne ſaluation, than of other mens: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God is vnto me a witnes of my calling, as alſo to euery one of the elect: touching others we haue no teſtimony, but from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward effect of the ſpirit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is ſo farre as the grace of God do ſhewe it ſelfe forth in them, vnto our knowledge. There is therefore a great difference: for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinty of faith remaineth cloſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in, &amp; diſperſe not it ſelf to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but wherſoeuer we behold, what tokens of God his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection may be apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by vs, forthwith we muſt be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to conceiue a good hope, as wel leſt we ſhould be enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous toward our neighbours, &amp; depriue them of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> equal &amp; ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle iudgement of loue: as alſo that they ſhould be thankfull vnto God. But this is a generall rule, as wel in vs as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that diſtruſting our owne ſtrength, we ſhould altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther depend vpon God only. <hi>Vntil the day of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> This is eſpecially to be vnderſtood vnto the end of their ſtriuing, &amp; that ſtriuing is ended by death: but becauſe the ſpirite is ſo wont to ſpeake in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt comming of Chriſt: it ſhall be better to extend the procéeding of grace, vnto the reſurrection of the fleſh: for although they that are deliuered out of this mortal body, fight no more with the luſtes of the fleſh, &amp; are without daunger of the weapon (as they ſay) yet it ſhall be no abſurditie, if they be ſayd to be in the way go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward: for as yet they are not come whether they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, as yet they doe not enioy that happines and glorye which they haue hoped for: finally, that daye hath not yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7789:7"/> ſhined, which ſhould reueale the treaſures hidden in hope. So when we ſpeake of hope, we muſt alwaies turne our eies vnto the bleſſed reſurrection, as vnto a marke.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </bibl> As it becommeth me ſo to iudge of you all, becauſe I haue you in my hart, that you all were partakers of my grace, both in my bands, and in my defence, and confirmation of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8</hi>
                     </bibl> For God is my witnes how I deſire you all, in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>9</hi>
                     </bibl> And this I pray, that your loue may abound yet more and more in knowledge, and in all iudgement.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>10</hi>
                     </bibl> That ye may allow thoſe things that are excellent, that ye may be pure and without offence, vntill the day of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>11</hi>
                     </bibl> Filled with the fruites of righteouſnes, which are by Ieſus Chriſt vnto the glorie and praiſe of God.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 <hi>As it becommeth me</hi>
                  </hi> For we are malicious interpreters of the gifts of God: we accompt none for the ſonnes of God, but them in whome the true ſignes of godlines appeare, to whome the ſpirit of adoption ſheweth forth him ſelfe by his fruites. Therfore <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth: that equitie it ſelfe doth teach him this, that he ſhould for euer hope well of the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> whome he ſawe to be ioyned into the participation of grace with him ſelfe. I haue not raſhly tranſlated this place otherwiſe than <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> which the wiſe reader ſhall eaſily perceiue: for he rehearſeth what iudgement he had of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> which was the cauſe why he did hope well of them. Therefore he ſayth, that they were partakers with him of the ſame grace in his bands, and in his defence of the Goſpell. <hi>To haue them in his hart,</hi> is to accompt them ſuch in the inward affection of his hart: for the <hi>Philippians</hi> to their power, were alwaies preſent with <hi>Paule,</hi> that ſo much as they could, they might be companions with him, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the cauſe of the Goſpell. So though they were farre of in body, yet for their kind affection, which they had teſtified vnto him by all poſſible duties, he acknowledgeth them to be in bands with him. I haue you therefore in my hart, that is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7789:7"/> ſincerely, and without diſſembling. Truly, not with a light and doubtfull opinion. Whome? <hi>The partakers of my grace.</hi> In what thing? <hi>In bands,</hi> whereby the Goſpell is defended. Since he acknowledged them to be ſuch men, it was méete to hope well of them. <hi>Of my grace, and in my bands.</hi> Before the world this were ridiculous, to accompt impriſonment for a benefit of God, but if we truely eſtéeme it, it is no common honor, wherewith God vouchſafeth vs, when we ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for his truth: neither in vaine was it ſayd: Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall you be when men ſhall all maner of wayes reuile and trouble you for my names ſake. <hi>Matth. 5.11.</hi> Let vs therfore remember that the fellowſhip of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe of Chriſt, as a ſingular grace of God, is with a cherefull and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mind to be embraced of vs. To his bands he addeth, <hi>The defence and confirmation of the Goſpell,</hi> that he might the better expreſſe how honorable a dutie the Lord enioineth vs, when he oppoſeth vs againſt his enimies, to giue teſtimonie vnto his Goſpell. For it is as if he ſhould commaund vnto vs the patronage of his Goſpell. With this cogitation Martyrs being armed, haue bene able to contemne all the rage of the wicked, and to ouercome all their torments: And I would to God this were in the mindes of all them, that are called to confeſſe the faith, that they are Patrons choſen by Chriſt to pleade his cauſe. For being ſtayed vpon ſuch a comfort, they would be more couragious than eaſily to be turned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully to fall from God. But ſome man will aſke here, whether the confirmation of the Goſpell depend vpon the conſtancie of men? I anſwer, that the truth of God is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of it ſelfe, than that it néedeth any other way to be vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. For we all are liers, yet God remaineth true: yet it is not abſurd, that weake conſciences by ſuch helpes ſhould be confirmed. Therfore this kind of confirmation which <hi>Paule</hi> remembreth, hath relation vnto men, as we learne by our owne experience: this at the leaſt is come to paſſe by the ſlaughters of ſo many Martyrs, that the Goſpell is ſealed in our harts as it were by ſo many ſeales. Whereof commeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7789:8"/> that of <hi>Tertullian:</hi> that their bloud is the ſéede of the Church, whome I alſo haue imitated in a verſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The holy bloud of martyrd Saincts</l>
                  <l>which God his honor defend,</l>
                  <l>Is like the ſeede caſt into earth</l>
                  <l>which great encreaſe forth ſend.</l>
               </q>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 <hi>For God is my witnes.</hi>
                  </hi> Nowe he declareth more plainly his loue toward them: for proofe whereof he addeth an othe: and that iuſtly, becauſe we knowe how deare the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vp of the Church is vnto God. It was very neceſſary, that the loue of <hi>Paule</hi> ſhould ſufficiently be teſtified vnto the <hi>Philippians:</hi> neither is this of ſmall force to procure credite vnto the doctrine, when the people is perſwaded that they are beloued of their teacher. He calleth God to be a witnes of the truth, who alone is truth, and to be a witnes of his affection, who alone is the ſearcher of the hartes. In this worde <hi>Deſire,</hi> the ſpeciall worde is put for the generall: it is a ſigne of loue, becauſe we deſire the thinges we loue. <hi>In our bowells.</hi> He oppoſeth the bowells of Chriſt vnto carnall affection, that he might ſignifie his loue to be holye and godlye: for he that loueth according to the fleſh, hath reſpect of his owne profite, and may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after according to the alteration of things and time change his minde: in the meane ſeaſon he admoniſheth by what rule the affections of the faithful ſhould be examined: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that forſaking their owne will, they ſhould ſuffer Chriſt to gouerne them. And certainly true loue can not procéede from any other thing, than from the bowels of Chriſt: and this pricke ſhould not lightly touch vs: that Chriſt doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort open his bowells, whereby he might cheariſh mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall loue amongeſt vs.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 <hi>This I pray, that your loue, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> He commeth agayne vnto his prayer, which by the waye he had in one worde touched afore. He ſheweth them therefore the ſumme of thoſe thinges which he beſéeched of God for them, that they them ſelues alſo by his example, might learne to praye, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7789:8"/> aſpire to the increaſe of theſe giftes. Whereas ſome doe take the loue of the <hi>Philippians,</hi> for the <hi>Philippians</hi> them ſelues, as commonly barbarous men are woont to ſpeake: ſauing your reuerence, your worſhip, it is abſurd: for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there anye ſuch example extant in <hi>Paule,</hi> neyther had ſuch fooliſhnes as yet come into cuſtome, beſide the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſhoulde not be full, and otherwiſe the ſimple and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall meaning of the wordes doth very well agrée: for the true encreaſe of Chriſtians, is when they goe forward in knowledge and vnderſtanding, and afterward in loue: therefore this worde <hi>In,</hi> according to the phraſe of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe tongue, is taken here for <hi>with,</hi> as I haue alſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated it: except ſome had rather expound it, <hi>By,</hi> that it ſhould ſignifie the inſtrument, or the formall cauſe: for the greater increaſe we make in knowledge, the more ſhould loue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in vs. Then the ſenſe were: that your loue ſhoulde encreaſe according to the meaſure of your vnderſtanding. <hi>All vnderstanding,</hi> is taken for full and ſounde vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, not for the vnderſtanding of all things.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 <hi>That ye may allowe.</hi>
                  </hi> The definition of Chriſtian wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, is to knowe that that is to the purpoſe, or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not to diſquiet the witte in vayne ſubtilties and ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, for the Lorde will not employe his ſeruantes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitably, leaſt they ſhoulde learne that which ſhoulde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing auayle them. Hereof you may gather, in what eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation the diuinitie of the Sorbonicall Sophiſters is to be had, wherein if thou ſpendeſt thy whole life, thou ſhalt no more be edified touching the hope of euerlaſting life, nor reape anye more ſpirituall profite, than out of the demonſtrations of <hi>Euclides.</hi> Truely, although it did teache no falſe thing: yet for this cauſe it ſhoulde worthily be accurſed, becauſe the profaning of ſpirituall doctrine, is verye daungerous: for the Scripture as <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth, is profitable. <hi>2. Tim. 3.16.</hi> There we can finde nothing but colde diſputations about trifles. <hi>That ye may be pure.</hi> This is the profit which we reape by knowledge, not that euery
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7789:9"/> man ſhould craftilye prouide for his owne eſtate, but that we ſhould liue with a pure conſcience before God. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: <hi>And without offence.</hi> The Gréeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is of doubtfull ſignification. <hi>Ghryſoſtome</hi> doth expounde it actiuely: that like as before God he would haue vs pure and innocent: ſo nowe before men he would haue vs leade an honeſt life: leſt by any euill examples they ſhould hurt their neighbours. This I reiect not: yet in my iudgement, the paſſiue ſignification agréeth better with the text: for to this ende did he wiſh them wiſedome, that with blameles ſteppes they ſhould goe forward in their vocation, vntil the day of Chriſt: as contrariwiſe by ignorance it commeth to paſſe, that oftentimes we fall, ſtumble, and goe aſtray. And how many offences Satan obiecteth vnto vs, which might either breake of our courſe, or hinder it, euery one of vs for him ſelfe haue experience. <hi>11 <hi>Filled with the fruites of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes.</hi>
                  </hi> This nowe pertaineth vnto the outward life: for a good conſcience bringeth forth her fruite by her workes: therefore he deſireth that they ſhould be fruitefull in good workes, vnto the glorie of God. Such fruites he ſayth are thorough Chriſt, becauſe they procéede from the grace of Chriſt: for this is vnto vs the beginning of well doing, when we are ſanctified by his ſpirite: for it reſted vpon him, that of his fulnes we all might receiue. And becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> here taketh a ſimilitude from trées: we are wild oliues and vnprofitable, vntill we are ingraffed into Chriſt, who by his liuing roote doth make vs fruitfull trees, according to that in <hi>Iohn. 15.1.</hi> I am the vine, you are the branches. He ſheweth alſo the ende, that we ſhould ſerue to the glorie of God: for no life is ſo excellent in ſhewe, which is not pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſtinketh before God, except it be directed vnto this marke. Wheras <hi>Paule</hi> here nameth righteouſnes of works, it maketh nothing againſt the frée righteouſnes of faith: for it doth not followe by and by that there is righteouſnes, where there are the fruites of righteouſnes, becauſe that righteouſnes before God is no other thing, than a full and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7789:9"/> ſound obedience of the lawe, which is found in none of the Saincts: who notwithſtanding according to their meaſure of grace, doe bring forth good and ſwéete fruites of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes: that is to ſay, becauſe God beginneth in vs righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes by the regeneration of his ſpirite: ſo that which wanteth, he ſupplieth by the remiſſion of ſinnes, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes neuertheles ſhould altogether depend vpon faith.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>12</hi>
                     </bibl> I would haue you knowe brethren, that the things which haue come vnto me, are turned rather to the furtherance of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>13</hi>
                     </bibl> So that my bands in Chriſt are famous in all the iudgement hall, and in all other places.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>14</hi>
                     </bibl> And many of the brethren in the Lord, boldened by my bands, dare more frankely ſpeake the word without feare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>15</hi>
                     </bibl> Some thorough enuie and contention, and ſome alſo of good will preach Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>16</hi>
                     </bibl> Some I ſay of contention preach Chriſt, not purely, ſuppoſing to adde more affliction to my bands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </bibl> But the other of loue, knowing that I am ſet for the defence of the Goſpell.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 <hi>I would haue you know.</hi>
                  </hi> We all haue experience in our ſelues, how much the fleſh is wont to be offended by the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie of the croſſe We ſuffer Chriſt to be preached vnto vs crucified, but when he appeareth with his croſſe, as if we were amaſed with ſome new ſight, either we runne away, or are afraid, and not onely in our owne perſons, but alſo in the perſons of them which deliuer the Goſpell vnto vs. It might haue happened vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of their Apoſtle, they might ſomewhat haue bene caſt downe: and it is credible, that euill laborers which ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for euery litle occaſion to hurt, did not ceaſe to reioyce at the calamitie of the good man, and thereof did make his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell to be deſpiſed. And if by this meanes they could not profit, they were ready to reuile him, becauſe he was hated of the whole world, and alſo to put a feare into the <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pians,</hi> leaſt by his vnluckie fellowſhip, they ſhould procure
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7789:10"/> vnto them ſelues great enuie without cauſe amongeſt all men: for theſe are the vſuall ſubtilties of ſatan. The Apoſtle méeteth with this danger, whileſt he rehearſeth that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell is furthered by his bands. The ende therefore of this narration, is to encourage the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that they ſhould not be afraid by his perſecution. <hi>13 <hi>So that my bands.</hi>
                  </hi> He put <hi>In Christ:</hi> for, in the buſines or in the cauſe of Chriſt: for he doth ſignifie, that his bands were famous to extoll the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of Chriſt. Whereas ſome doe expound it by Chriſt, it ſéemeth to be ſtrained, and I had rather haue it famous than manifeſt, becauſe the report of them brought honor to the Goſpell: as if he ſhould ſay, Satan went about this thing, and the vngodly thought it ſhould ſo come to paſſe, that the Goſpell ſhould be deſtroyed: but God hath made fruſtrate, as well his endeuors, as their hope, and that two manner of wayes: for when before the Goſpell was obſcure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne vnto many, it is come to paſſe, that it is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: and not that onely, but alſo, that it is made famous, as well in the iudgement hall, as in the reſt of the citie. <hi>The iudgement hall, <hi>In caſtrum Praetorum,</hi>
                  </hi> I take for the Court and Pallaice of <hi>Nero,</hi> which <hi>Fabius,</hi> and the writers of that age, call <hi>Auguſtale.</hi> For when the name of <hi>Praetor</hi> was in the beginning generall, and did ſignifie all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates that had chiefe gouernment, (whereof it came to paſſe, that the <hi>Dictator</hi> was called the chiefe <hi>Praetor</hi>) the cuſtome afterwarde remained: that in warre the tent ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Conſul,</hi> or of him that was Generall, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Praetorium:</hi> but in the citie, the pallaice of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> of whom the Emperours tooke their Monarchie: otherwiſe <hi>Praetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> is alſo called the Seſſion of the <hi>Praetor. Many of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> By this example we are taught, that the vexations of the Sainctes which they ſuffer for the Goſpell, is vnto vs a cauſe of confidence. It were in déede a terrible ſpectacle, and which would rather tende to exanimate vs, if we ſhoulde onely beholde the crueltie and rage of the perſecutors: but whileſt the hande of the Lorde appeareth, which vnder the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7789:10"/> infirmitye of the croſſe, doth make his ſeruants inuincible, and to triumphe: truſting hereunto we muſt be more bolde than we are woont, hauing alreadye in the perſon of our brethren, the pledge of our victorie. The acknowledging here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ought to ouercome our feare, that in the middes of dangers we ſhould ſpeake without trembling. <hi>15 <hi>Some truly.</hi>
                  </hi> An other fruite of the bands of <hi>Paule,</hi> becauſe not onely the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren were encouraged to ſtand ſtedfaſt in their faith, by his example, and others to ſtande in their eſtate, others were made more chearefull to teach: but alſo they that wiſhed him ill, by an other counſell were prouoked to publiſh the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16 <hi>Some I ſay of contention.</hi>
                  </hi> An explanation, whereby he declareth more fully the former ſentence: for he repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth two kindes of men, who by his bands were prouoked to preache Chriſt. Some were ſtirred vp by contention, that is by en euill affection: ſome other by a godly deſire, becauſe they together would take vpon them the defence of the Goſpell. They, he ſayth, did not preach Chriſt pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe their zeale was not aright. Neither doe this pertaine vnto doctrine, becauſe it may be, that he that teacheth moſte ſincerely, is not of a ſincere minde, but that this was a corruption of the minde, and did not appeare in doctrine, we maye gather out of the text. <hi>Paule</hi> truelye woulde not willingly haue ſéene the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell diſſembled with: yet he teſtifieth that he reioyceth in the preaching of theſe men, the which was neyther ſimple nor ſincere. But a queſtion may be aſked, how ſuch prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching coulde hurt him? I aunſwere, that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny occaſions vnknowne vnto vs, who doe not conſider the circumſtances of tymes. Another queſtion is aſked, that ſince the Goſpell can not be preached but of them that vnderſtande it, what cauſe moued them to perſecute that doctrine which they allowed. I aunſwere that ambition is blind, yea a furious beaſt: therefore it is no maruell, if falſe brethren doe take occaſion cut of the Goſpell, to diſquiet the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7789:11"/> good and faithfull Paſtors. And truly <hi>Paule</hi> hath ſayd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here, which my ſelfe haue not tried: for as yet there liue ſome at this day, who haue preached the Goſpell with none other intent, than, that by perſecuting godly Paſtors, they might yéeld to the furie of the wicked. Touching <hi>Paule</hi> his enimies, it is not amiſſe to marke, if they were Iewes, how mad their hatred was, that euen they forgat for what cauſe they hated him: for whileſt they were carried away by hatred to deſtroy him, they laboured in promoting the Goſpell, for whoſe cauſe they were angry with him: but they thought verily that the cauſe of Chriſt ſhould either ſtand, or fall in the life of one man. But if they that were ſo ſeduced by ambition, were emulous among them ſelues: we muſt acknowledge the maruellous goodnes of God, who notwithſtanding gaue ſuch ſucceſſe to their peruerſe ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors. <hi>17 <hi>That I am ſet for the defence.</hi>
                  </hi> They that loued Chriſt truly, thought it a ſhame for them ſelues, if they did not ioyne with <hi>Paule</hi> as companions, pleading his cauſe, and ſo we muſt doe: we muſt ſuccor the ſeruants of Chriſt being in diſtreſſe, as much as we may. Marke againe this manner of ſpeach, of the defence of the Goſpell: for ſince Chriſt vouchſafeth vs ſuch honor, what excuſe can we haue, if we be faint harted in his cauſe? or what muſt we looke for, if we betray it by our ſilence, but that in like manner he ſhould forſake our cauſe, who alone is our Aduocate and Patrone with God his father.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </bibl> What then? yet all maner of waies, whether vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or truly Chriſt is preached: and in this I reioyce, and will reioyce.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </bibl> For I know, that this ſhall turne to my ſaluation, thorough your praier, and by the helpe of the ſpirite of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </bibl> According to my expectation, and hope, that in nothing I ſhall be aſhamed: but with all confidence, as alwaies, ſo now, Chriſt ſhall be magnified in my body, whether it be by life or death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </bibl> For Chriſt is to me both in life and in death aduantages</p>
               </q>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7789:11"/>
                  <hi>18 <hi>Yet all maner of waies.</hi>
                  </hi> Becauſe the wicked minde of them, of whome he ſpake, might ſlaunder the grace of the doctrine, he ſaith, that this is greatly to be eſtéemed, becauſe that they promoted the Goſpell notwithſtanding, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their intent was: for God by euill and wicked inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſometime bringeth to paſſe an excellent worke. Therefore he ſaith, he reioyceth for ſuch ſucceſſe, becauſe he was contented with this only, to ſée the kingdome of Chriſt encreaſe. As when we did heare that the vncleane dogge <hi>Charles,</hi> at <hi>Auenion</hi> and in other places, did ſowe the ſéedes of pure doctrine in manie mens hearts, we gaue thankes vnto God, who vſed this naughtie and deſperate varlet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his owne glorie. And at this day, we reioice that the courſe of the Goſpell is promoted by manie, who haue a far other purpoſe. But although <hi>Paule</hi> did reioice for the encreaſe of the Goſpell, yet would he neuer haue ordained ſuch miniſters, if it had béene in hys power. We muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reioice, if by the vngodly God worketh any good: yet we muſt neither place ſuch in the miniſterie, nor accompt them for the lawfull miniſters of Chriſt. <hi>19 <hi>For I knowe.</hi>
                  </hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome did publiſh the Goſpell, to procure enuie vnto <hi>Paule,</hi> that they might the more incenſe the crueltie of hys enemies againſt him: he anſwereth by a <hi>Praeocupation,</hi> that their wicked purpoſes ſhall not hurt him, becauſe God will turne them to a contrary end, as if he ſhould ſay: Although they imagine my deſtruction, yet I truſt that all their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes ſhall doo nothing elſe, but that Chriſt in me may bée glorified, which turneth vnto my ſaluation. For that hée ſpeaketh not of the ſafetie of his bodie, it is euident by that which follow. But from whence had <hi>Paule</hi> this confidence? truely from that which he teacheth <hi>Rom. 8, 28.</hi> Vnto the true worſhippers of God all things helpe to their good, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the whole world with their Prince the Diuell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire their deſtruction. <hi>By your prayer.</hi> That he might the more earneſtly prouoke them to pray, he affirmeth, that hée truſteth the Lord will graunt it by their praiers. Neyther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7789:12"/> doth he diſſemble: for he that repoſeth ſuccour in the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Sainctes, ſtayeth vpon the promiſe of God: and yet nothing is derogated from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free goodnes of God, wherby our prayers and ſupplications are made. <hi>And by the helpe of the Spirite.</hi> Leſt we ſhoulde thinke that becauſe he ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth theſe two thinges in the text, therefore they are equal: the ſentence muſt therefore thus be reſolued: I knowe that all this ſhall turne to my ſaluation by the furtherance of the ſpirite, you helping by your prayers: ſo that the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſpirite is the efficient cauſe, and prayer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior helper. The propertie alſo of the Gréeke worde is to be noted: for it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, when that is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed which is wanting, according to which ſignification, the ſpirite of God powreth vpon vs all thinges whereof we are deſtitute. He nameth <hi>The ſpirite of Ieſus Christ,</hi> to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie that he is common vnto vs all, if we be Chriſtians, becauſe the ſpirite was powred vpon him in all fulnes, that he might diſtribute to euery one of his members, according to the meaſure of his grace, ſo much as is expedient.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20 <hi>According to my expectation.</hi>
                  </hi> If anie ſhoulde obiect, whence haue you this knowledge? he aunſwereth from hope: for ſince it is certaine that God will not ſuffer our hope to be fruſtrate, our hope muſt in no caſe be doubtfull. Therfore let the godly reader marke diligently this aduerb, <hi>According,</hi> that he may ſo certainly be reſolued with him ſelfe, that it can not be, but the Lorde muſt aunſwere our expectation, which is grounded in his worde: for he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that he will neuer forſake vs, no not in the middeſt of all torments, if at anye tyme we be called to the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his name: therefore let all the godly hope by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Paule,</hi> and they ſhall not be aſhamed. <hi>With all confidence.</hi> We ſée that by hoping, he doth not yéeld to the deſires of the fleſhe, but ſubmitteth his hope to the promiſe of God. <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſayth, <hi>ſhall be magnified in my bodye, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by life, or death.</hi> Although expreſſing his bodye namely, he ſignifieth that among the combates of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7789:12"/> life, he is not doubtfull of the ſucceſſe: for of this thing God hath aſſured vs: therefore if we be framed to the will of God, and haue the ſame purpoſe in our life, that <hi>Paule</hi> had, we hope for an happie ende howſoeuer: we néede no more to feare leſt anye euill ſhould happen vnto vs: for if we liue and dye to him, in life and death we are his. <hi>Rom. 14.8.</hi> He ſheweth a manner howe to magnifie Chriſt, namely in a perfect confidence: whereof it followeth, that he is caſt downe by our fault, and extenuated as much as is in vs, when we faint thorough feare. Are not they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſhamed, who thinke it a light fault to be afraide in the confeſſion of the truth? but howe ſhoulde they be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when they are ſo impudent, that they dare alſo excuſe the deniall of Chriſt. He addeth, <hi>As alwayes,</hi> that by the experiments of the grace of God already paſt, they might confirme their faith. So in the <hi>Rom. 5.4.</hi> Triall bringeth hope.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>21 <hi>For in life.</hi>
                  </hi> Hitherto in my iudgement, the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters haue ill tranſlated and expounded this place: for thus they diſtinguiſh, that Chriſt was vnto <hi>Paule</hi> life, and death was to him aduantage. But I make Chriſt the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in both the members of the ſentence, that as well in life as in death, he is ſayde to be aduantage: for it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Grecians to vnderſtand this prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which ſignifie to. But beſide, that this ſence is not ſtrained, it agréeth alſo better with the next ſentence, and containeth more plentifull doctrine. He affirmeth that he is indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, whether he liue or dye, becauſe that hauing Chriſt, he accompteth gaine in both: and truely it is onely Chriſt that in death and life maketh vs bleſſed: otherwiſe, if the death be miſerable, the life is no whit the happier. So that it is harde to define whether it be better for a man to lyue, or to dye without Chriſt. Agayne, let Chriſt be preſent, and he will bleſſe both our lyfe and our death, that both of them ſhall bée happye and good for vs.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7789:13"/>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>22</hi>
                     </bibl> But if to liue in the fleſh were more profitable for me: euen what to chooſe I knowe not:</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>23</hi>
                     </bibl> For I am distreſſed betweene both, deſiring to be looſed and to be with Chriſt which is farre better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>34</hi>
                     </bibl> But to abide in the fleſh is more needefull for you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>25</hi>
                     </bibl> And this am I ſure of, that I ſhall abide and continue with you all for your furtherance and ioy of your faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>26</hi>
                     </bibl> That your reioycing may be abundant in Chriſt Ieſus for me, by my comming vnto you agayne.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22 <hi>But if to liue.</hi>
                  </hi> Euen as deſperate men are in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie whether they ſhould ſtill prolong their life in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or finiſh their ſorrowes by death: ſo contrarywiſe, <hi>Paule</hi> with an equall mind ſaith, that he is prepared as well for death as for life, becauſe the eſtate of both is bleſſed vnto the faithfull, ſo that he is doubtfull whether to chooſe. <hi>If it be profitable,</hi> that is to ſaie, if I knowe that the profite of my life is greater than the profite of my death, I ſée not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhoulde rather deſire. He putteth, <hi>To liue in the fleſhe.</hi> by a contempt, in compariſon of a better life. <hi>23 <hi>For I am distreſſed.</hi> Paule</hi> did not deſire to lyue for anie other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, then to ſerue to the glorie of Chriſte, and to profite hys brethren. Therefore hée eſtéemeth no other profite in thys lyfe, than the ſaluation of hys brethren: but for hymſelfe priuately hée acknowledgeth that it is better to dye quicklie, becauſe hée ſhoulde bée wyth Chriſt. In hys deſire hée ſheweth with how great loue hée is enflamed. Hée doth not ſpeake héere of earthlie commodities, but of the ſpirituall good, which eſpeciallie of the godlie is careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to be wiſhed for. Notwithſtanding <hi>Paule,</hi> as it were forgetting hymſelfe, doth not onely contayne himſelfe in the middeſt, leaſt he ſhould more decline to his owne bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, than the benefite of the <hi>Philippians:</hi> but at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, that he weigheth theyr eſtate in his heart. And this is truely to liue and dye vnto Chriſt, when neglecting our ſelues, we are carried whether Chriſt calleth vs. <hi>Deſiring to be loſed and to be with Chriſt.</hi> Theſe two things are iointly to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7789:13"/> be read together, for death of it ſelfe will neuer be wiſhed for, becauſe the deſire thereof fighteth with the ſence of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but it is deſired for ſome cauſe, or for ſome other ende. Deſperate men flie vnto it thorough wearines of their life, but the faithfull haſten vnto it willingly, becauſe it deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them from the bondage of ſinne, and is a paſſage vnto the kingdome of heauen. This is it that <hi>Paule</hi> now ſayth: I deſire to dye, becauſe by this meanes I ſhall come to be ioyned with Chriſt: yet the faithfull ceaſe not to be afraide of death, but when they turne their eyes vnto that life that followeth after death, by this conſolation they eaſily ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come that feare. Truely whoſoeuer beléeueth in Chriſt, ſhould be ſo couragious, that at the mention of death he ſhould lift vp his head, being ioyfull for the tidings of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption: whereby it appeareth how many are Chriſtians onely in name, when the greater part hearing the mention of death, as if they neuer had heard any word of Chriſt: they doe not onely waxe fearefull, but become almoſt deade. O a good conſcience? how much doſt thou excell? and how much doeſt thou preuaile? but faith is the foundation of a good conſcience: yea <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the conſcience. <hi>To be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued.</hi> This manner of ſpeaking is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> men call death the deſtruction of man, as though the whole man periſhed. <hi>Paule</hi> here warneth vs, that death is diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule from the bodie: and this ſtraight after he expreſſeth better, ſhewing what the eſtate of the faithfull is after death: namely that they abide and dwell with Chriſt. We are alſo with Chriſt in this life, ſo farre as his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is within vs, and Chriſt dwelleth in vs by faith, and he hath promiſed that he will be with vs euen vnto the ende of the world: but that preſence we onely perceiue by hope: therefore according to our féeling, we are ſayd to be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from him. <hi>2. Cor. 5.6.</hi> This place is of force to refute the dotage of them, who dreame that the ſoules diuided from the bodies are aſléepe: for <hi>Paule</hi> witneſſeth openly, that we enioy the preſence of Chriſt, when we are diſſolued.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:7789:14"/>
                  <hi>25 <hi>And this am I ſure of.</hi>
                  </hi> Some becauſe it ſéemed abſurd, that the Apoſtle ſhould confeſſe him ſelfe to be fruſtrate of his expectation, thinke that he was afterward deliuered out of bands, and that he paſſed thorough many regions of the world: but in vaine doe they feare that. For the Saincts are woont to moderate their hope by the worde of God, that in their mindes they preſume no more than the Lorde hath promiſed. So, where they haue a ſure teſtimonie of God his will, there they ſtay them ſelues with a certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, which admitteth no doubt. Such is the perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the continuall remiſſion of ſinnes, of the helpe of the Spirite vnto the grace of finall perſeuerance (as they call it) of the reſurrection of the fleſhe. Such alſo was the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of the Prophets, touching their propheſies: in other things they hope nothing but with a condition, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſubmit all the ſucceſſe vnto the prouidence of God, to whom they graunt to haue a ſharper ſight in things, than them ſelues. <hi>To abide,</hi> ſignifie here for a litle while. <hi>To conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,</hi> ſignifie for a longe time.</p>
               <p n="26">
                  <hi>26 <hi>That your reioycing.</hi>
                  </hi> Wheras he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> twiſe in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ence. No body will deny, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faithfully I haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the mind of <hi>Paule.</hi> But wheras ſome do ſay, <hi>By Chriſt:</hi> I like it not: for <hi>In Chriſt,</hi> is put for after Chriſt, or Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anlike, that he might ſhew the kind of reioycing to be holy: for otherwiſe we are commaunded to reioyce onely in God: therfore might it be obiected to <hi>Paule</hi> by the malicious, how is it lawfull for the <hi>Philippians</hi> to reioyce for thée? he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth this ſlander, when he ſayeth, that they ſhall doe it thorough Chriſt: that is to ſay, reioycing for the ſeruant of Chriſt, vnto the glorie of the Lorde: and that rather in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the doctrine, than of the man, and againſt the falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as <hi>Dauid</hi> in comparing himſelfe with hypocrites, boaſteth of his owne righteouſnes.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>27</hi>
                     </bibl> Onely walke you worthy of the Goſpell of Chriſt, that whether I come and ſee you, or els be abſent, I maye
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7789:14"/> heare of you, that ye abide in one ſpirite, in one minde, fighting together thorough the faith of the Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>28</hi>
                     </bibl> And in nothing feare your aduerſaries, which is to them a declaration of their deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to you of ſaluation, and that from God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>29</hi>
                     </bibl> Becauſe it is giuen you for Chriſt, that not onely ye ſhould beleeue in him, but alſo ſuffer for his ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>30</hi>
                     </bibl> Hauing the ſame ſtrife, which ye ſaw to be in me, and now heare of me.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="27">
                  <hi>27 <hi>Onely walke worthy.</hi>
                  </hi> We vſe this phraſe, when we would paſſe ouer vnto a newe ſpeach, and it is as much as if he would haue ſayd, for my ſelfe the Lord will prouide, but you, &amp;c. whatſoeuer become of me, yet notwithſtanding go you forward in a right courſe. Where he calleth a pure and honeſt conuerſation worthy the Goſpell: he argueth that contrariwiſe they doe iniurie to the Goſpel, that liue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <hi>That whether I come.</hi> Becauſe this ſentence of <hi>Paule</hi> in the Gréeke is hard by the participle <hi>ſeeing,</hi> I haue made it by the verbe, <hi>And ſee.</hi> If this like you not, vnderſtand the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall verbe, <hi>That I may vnderſtand:</hi> in this ſenſe, whether I come and ſée you, or being abſent ſhall heare of your eſtate, I may vnderſtand both waies, as wel by ſight, as by meſſage, that you continue in one ſpirite, but we muſt litle care for words, where the meaning is euident. <hi>That ye abide in one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi> This truely is one of the chiefe vertues of the Church, and therefore this is the onely reaſon to cheariſh ſoundnes, becauſe it falleth to ruine by diſſention. Although <hi>Paule</hi> by this, as it were by a receit againſt poiſon, would méete with new and ſtrange doctrines: yet he requireth a double vnitie, of the ſpirite, and of the minde: for this is the chiefeſt thing we ſhould agrée among our ſelues, than that we ſhould be at concord. For where theſe two words are ioyned together, the ſpirit ſignifie vnderſtanding, and the minde do ſignifie wil. Conſent goeth before in order, then coniunction of wils procéedeth from that <hi>Fighting together thorough faith.</hi> This is the ſtrong bond of concorde, whileſt we muſt fight together
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7789:15"/> vnder one banner: for this occaſion many tymes haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled greateſt enimies. Therfore that he might the more confirme the vnitie among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Philippians,</hi> he warneth them that they are fellow ſouldies: that their enimie and their warre is common to them all, and that they muſt ioyne their mindes in an holie vnitie. The ſpeache that <hi>Paule</hi> vſeth in the Gréeke is doubtfull: wherefore an olde Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter hath turned it: <hi>Labouring together thorough faith. <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
                  </hi> hath, <hi>Helping forward your faith.</hi> As if they ſhould helpe faith ſo much as they might. But ſince the datiue caſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Grecians, is put for the ablatiue caſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, becauſe that tongue wanteth an ablatiue caſe: I doubt not but this is the meaning of the Apoſtle. Let the faith of the Goſpell ioyne you together in vnitie, eſpecially ſince that is your common armour againſt that ſame eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. By this meanes I referre the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> which other referre vnto faith, and better, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I be deceiued: firſt of all no man is ignorant, how for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible the prouocation vnto concord is, when as like fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes we muſt fight together: beſides we know in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall warre, that we are armed with the ſhield of faith, to beate backe our enimie: yea faith is our complete armour &amp; our victorie: therefore he addeth alſo this part, that he might ſhewe the ende of godly vnitie: the wicked alſo conſpire to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnto miſchiefe, but their conſent is accurſed: let vs therefore with one minde warre together vnder the banner of faith. <hi>And in nothing feare.</hi> The ſecond thing that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> is courage of minde, that they ſhould not be troubled for the rage of their aduerſaries. At that time cruel perſecutions were hot almoſt in euery place, becauſe Satan was carried forth with all violence to hinder the beginnings of the Goſpell: but he did rage ſo much the more weakely, by how much the more ſtrongly Chriſt did ſhew forth the grace of his ſpirite. Therefore he biddeth the <hi>Philippians</hi> to ſtand without feare, and not to be troubled. <hi>Which vnto them is a declaration</hi> This is the proper ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7789:15"/> of the Gréeke word, and no reaſon compelled others to tranſlate it, a <hi>Cauſe:</hi> for the vngodly whileſt they warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, they declare, as it were by a preamble, the argument of their owne deſtruction: and the more fiercely they inſult vpon the godly, ſo much the more they prepare them ſelues to their owne fall. The Scripture in no place doth teach, that the afflictions which the Saincts doe ſuffer of the wicked, is a cauſe of their ſaluation, but a <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or an <hi>argument. Paule</hi> alſo calleth it in an other place, <hi>2. Theſ. 1.5.</hi> and in ſtead of the worde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which we haue here, he vſeth there <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This therefore is a ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, that whileſt we are iniuried or vexed by our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, we haue a document of our owne ſaluation: for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions are vnto the ſonnes of God certaine ſeales of their adoption, if they beare them valiantly &amp; with equal minds: the vngodly nowe ſhewe forth a token of their damnation, becauſe they ſtumble againſt that ſtone which ſhall grinde them to powder. <hi>And that from God.</hi> This is reſtrained vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the latter part: that the taſte of God his grace might mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the bitternes of the croſſe. Naturally no man will take a ſigne or declaration of his ſaluation to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, for they are things in a manner contrary. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> calleth backe the <hi>Philippians,</hi> vnto an other conſideration: namely, that God by his bleſſing turneth thoſe things into an occaſion of ſaluation, which otherwiſe ſéeme to make vs miſerable. He proueth this: becauſe ſuffering of the croſſe is the gift of God: but it is certaine, that all the gifts of God turne to our ſaluation. To you he ſayth it is giuen, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ye ſhould beléeue in him, but alſo ſuffer for his ſake: therefore your very ſufferings are teſtimonies vnto you of the grace of God. Since it is ſo, from hence you haue an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of your ſaluation. Oh that this perſuaſion were tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly ſetled in our minds, that perſecutions are to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefits of God, how then would we grow forward in the doctrine of godlines? notwithſtanding what is more certaine, than that it is a great glorie of the grace of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7789:16"/> God, that we ſuffer for his name, either reproch, or inpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, or ſorrowes, or torments, or laſtly death it ſelfe: for then the Lord doth bewtifie vs with his owne enſignes. But there ſhall more be found that will rather bid God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part with ſuch gifts, than would thankfully embrace the croſſe being offered: woe worth our dulnes.</p>
               <p n="29">
                  <hi>29 <hi>That ye ſhould beleeue.</hi>
                  </hi> He hath wiſely conuerted faith with the croſſe, by an inſeparable knot, that the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians</hi> might knowe, that they were called, vpon this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, vnto the faith of Chriſt, that they ſhould ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions for his name: as if he ſhould ſay, their adoption can no more be ſeparated from the croſſe, than Chriſt him ſelfe can be pulled from them. Here <hi>Paule</hi> doth manifeſtly wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that both faith and conſtancie in ſuffering perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is the free gift of God. And truly the knowledge of God is an higher wiſedome, than that we can attaine vnto it by our owne wit: and our weakenes doe ſhew it ſelfe by daily experience, when God a litle withdraweth his hand from vs. And that he might the better expreſſe, that both theſe are the frée giftes of God, he ſpeaketh, namely that they are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs for Chriſt his ſake, or by the grace of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he excludeth all reſpect of merite. This place alſo make againſt the opinion of the Schoolemen, wherein they teach, that the latter graces are the rewardes of our merit, becauſe we haue vſed the firſt aright. Truely I doe not deny, but the Lorde doth reward in vs the right vſe of his graces, with more ample graces, ſo that thou doſt not oppoſe thine owne merite againſt his frée liberalitie, and againſt the merite of Chriſt, which they doe.</p>
               <p n="30">
                  <hi>30 <hi>Hauing the ſame ſtrife.</hi>
                  </hi> By his owne example alſo, he confirmeth that which he ſayd, which addeth no litle au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie vnto his doctrine. And he admoniſheth them, that thoſe workes are no cauſe why they ſhould be troubled at his bonds, looking for the ende of their ſtrife.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:7789:16"/>
               <head>Chap. 2.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1</hi>
                        </bibl> 
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F therefore there be any conſolation in Christ: if anye comfort of loue: if any fellowſhip of the ſpirite: if any bowels, and mercy.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2</hi>
                        </bibl> Fulfill my ioy, that ye may thinke the ſame thing, hauing loue, being of one mind, and of one iudgement.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>3</hi>
                        </bibl> That nothing be done thorough contention or vaine glorie: but that thorough humilitie euery man eſteeme others bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than him ſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>4</hi>
                        </bibl> Be not carefull euery man for his owne, but euery man alſo for the things of other men.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1 <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F therefore.</hi>
                  </hi> This exhortation is very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetical, wherein by all meanes he entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that they would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace mutual concord among them ſelues, leſt that if they ſhould be diuided by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, they ſhould be layde open to the illuſions of the falſe Apoſtles: for alwaies in diſſentions there is a gate open vnto ſatan, to ſpread vngodly doctrines, to repel the which, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent is the beſt defence. Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is oft times taken for exhortation, the beginning of the chapter might thus be expounded. If my exhortation, which is done in the name and by the commaundement of Chriſt, doth any thing preuail with you. Yet the other ſenſe doe better agrée with the text: if there be in you <hi>Any conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt,</hi> wherby you might mittigate my ſorrowes: and if you will any way comfort and eaſe me, which truly you ſhould do thorough loue: if you thinke vpon that fellowſhip of the ſpirit, which ſhould make vs all one: if any féeling of humanitie &amp; mercie remaineth in you, which might moue you to ſuccor my miſery, fulfil my ioy, &amp;c. Hereby we gather how great a good vnitie is in the Church, &amp; with how great care it is by the Paſtors to be procured. We muſt alſo mark how he humbleth him ſelfe, humbly intreating their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, who might by the dutie of a father haue exacted reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from them as from his ſonnes. He knew howe to vſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7789:17"/> commaunding when néede required: now he had rather vſe prayers, becauſe he knewe them more fit to pearce their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and becauſe he knew that he ſpake vnto them that were obedient, and eaſie to be taught. So the Paſtor muſt not refuſe to take vpon him any perſon for the Churches ſake.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 <hi>Fulfill my ioye.</hi>
                  </hi> And here we may perceiue howe litle carefull he was for him ſelfe, ſo that the Church of Chriſt were in good caſe. He was kept cloſe in priſon, and bound with chaines, he was condemned to looſe his heade: torments were before him, and the executioner at hand to diſpatch him: notwithſtanding all theſe did not hinder him, but that he did ſoundly reioyce to ſée the Churches flouriſh: furthermore he eſtéemeth this an eſpeciall thing in the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſtate of the Church, if there raigne mutuall conſent and brotherly concord among them. So the <hi>137.</hi> Pſalme teacheth vs, that the chiefe point of our ioy is the remembrance of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. And if that were the fulnes of <hi>Paule</hi> his ioye, the <hi>Philippians</hi> had bene more than cruell, if by diſſentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues, they ſhould haue tormented the hart of the holy man with a double ſorrowe. <hi>That ye may thinke the ſame thing.</hi> The ſumme is this, that in their opinions &amp; their wills they ſhould conſent. For he ſetteth downe conſent in doctrine and mutuall loue: then repeating the ſame thing (in my iudgement) he biddeth them be of one minde, and to thinke the ſame thing: theſe wordes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are of this force, that they ſhould apply them ſelues one to another: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the beginning of loue is to agrée in opinions: but that is not ſufficient, except the harts doe encreaſe together in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mutuall loue. Although it were not abſurd to tranſlate it thus: that you ſhould be of the ſame cogitation, to haue mutual loue, to be of one mind, and to thinke the ſame thing: for the participles are many times vſed for the Infinitiue moodes: yet I haue followed that ſenſe which ſéemed to be leſſe ſtrained.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 <hi>That nothing be done thorough contention</hi>
                  </hi> Theſe two are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7789:17"/> moſt hurtfull plagues to trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace of the Church. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ariſeth whileſt euery man wil ſtiffely defend his own opinion, and when it is once hote, it is carried headlong into that way where it entred: but vaine glorie tickleth the minds, ſo that euery man flattereth himſelf in his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions. Therefore this is the only reaſon to méete with diſſentions if we auoide ſtrife, by counſelling and diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching matters quietly, and eſpecially if we be not carried by ambition, for ambition is as it were the bellowes of diſcord. <hi>Vaine glorie</hi> ſignifieth all the glory of the fleſh: for what haue men wherein to reioice, but in vanity? <hi>But thorough humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> Againſt both theſe diſeaſes he ſetteth one remedie, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, and that not without cauſe, for it is the mother of modeſtie, whereby it commes to paſſe, that yéelding as it were ſomewhat of our owne right, we graunt it vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and rage not eaſily thorough diſſention. He defineth what true humilitie is, namely, when euery man preferreth others before himſelfe: and if any thing be hard in our whole life, this is eſpecially, therefore it is no maruell if humilitie be ſo rare a vertue, for (as he ſaith) euery man hath a kings mind in himſelfe, in challenging all things vnto himſelfe: behold the pride of nature. Then of the fooliſh admiration of our ſelues ſpringeth contempt of our brethren, and we are ſo farre from that which <hi>Paule</hi> héere commandeth, that ſcarſe anie man can ſuffer others to be equall with him, for there is no man that deſireth not to be aloft. But héere a queſtion ariſeth, how can it be that he, who in déede excelleth others, ſhould eſtéeme them better than himſelfe, whome hée knowe do come nothing néere him? I aunſwere, that all this dependeth vpon the right eſtimation of the giftes of God, and of our owne infirmities. For howſoeuer anie man excelleth in excellent gifts, he muſt thinke that they are not beſtowed vpon him to this end to pleaſe himſelfe, to exalt himſelfe, or to accompt of them, but he muſt exerciſe himſelfe in examining and acknowledging his owne vices, and ſo he ſhall haue large matter of humilitie. Contrarywiſe, he ſhall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7789:18"/> honour what vertues he ſéeth in other men, and ſhall bury their vices by loue: he that ſhall obſerue this rule, ſhall ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily preferre others before him ſelfe. And this is that which <hi>Paule</hi> would, when he added: that euery man ſhould not be carefull for them ſelues, but for their neighbours: or that they ſhould not onely be addicted to them ſelues. Therefore it may be that a godly man will haue more care of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things of other men, although he knoweth him ſelfe more excellent than they.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>5</hi>
                     </bibl> Let this minde be in you, that was euen in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>6</hi>
                     </bibl> Who, when he was in the forme of God, would haue thought it no robbery to be equall with God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </bibl> But he made him ſelfe of no reputation, taking the forme of a ſeruant, being made in the likenes of men, and in ſhape found as a man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8</hi>
                     </bibl> He humbled him ſelfe, I ſay, being made obedient to the death, euen the death of the croſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>9</hi>
                     </bibl> Wherefore God alſo hath exalted him on high, and giuen him a name which is aboue all names.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>10</hi>
                     </bibl> That in the name of Ieſus all knees ſhoulde bowe, of thinges in heauen, and thinges in earth, and things vnder the earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>11</hi>
                     </bibl> And all tongues ſhould confeſſe that Ieſus Christ is the Lord, vnto the glory of God the father.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 <hi>Let this mind be in you.</hi>
                  </hi> He commendeth now humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by the example of Chriſt, vnto the which he had exhorted them afore in words. There are two partes of the ſentence: in the former whereof, he inuiteth vs vnto the imitation of Chriſt, becauſe it is the rule of our life: in the ſecond he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureth vs, becauſe this is the way whereby we come vnto true glorie. Therefore he commaundeth euery one to haue the ſame affection that was in Chriſt. Afterward he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, what manner of example of humilitie is propounded vnto vs in Chriſt. I haue kept ſtill the paſſiue kinde of the verbe, although I miſlike not the tranſlation of others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7789:18"/> nothing is chaunged concerning the ſence: onely I would that the Readers ſhould hold that forme of ſpeaking, which <hi>Paule</hi> vſed.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 <hi>Who being in the forme of God.</hi>
                  </hi> It is no compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thinges like, but of the greater and the leſſe. The humilitie of Chriſt was to abaſe him ſelfe from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt toppe of glorie, vnto the vileſt reproche: our humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, not to exalt our ſelues with a falſe opinion of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. He yéelded of his right: of vs this onely is required, that we take no more to our ſelues, than it behoueth vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hence it ariſeth, that when he was in the forme of God, he thought it not vnlawfull for him, to behaue him ſelfe in that forme, but made him ſelfe of no accompt. Therfore how abſurd is it that the Sonne of God ſhould deſcend from ſo high a top of dignitie, and we that are nothing, ſhould be lifted vp with pride? the forme of God here ſignifieth his maieſtie: for as a man is knowne by the ſight of his forme: ſo the maieſtie that ſhineth in God, is the figure of him: or if thou hadſt rather haue a fitter ſimilitude, the forme of a King is the apparell and excellencie that ſheweth a King, as his ſcepter, his crowne, his robes, his Officers, his iudgement ſeate, and ſuch other enſignes of a kingdome: the forme of a Conſul, is his gowne, his noble apparell, his chayre of Iuorie, his Serieants with roddes, and axes. Chriſt therefore before the world was made, was in the forme of God, becauſe he had his glorie from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with his father: as he ſayth, <hi>Iohn. 17.5.</hi> for in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, before he put vpon him our fleſh, there was nothing baſe or abiect, but beſéeming the magnificence of God. When he was ſuch an one, he might without iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie beare him ſelf equal with God: but he did not ſhew what he was, neither did he openly in the ſight of men, take that which by right was his owne. <hi>He would haue thought it no robberie.</hi> It had bene no iniurie if he had appeared e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to God: for whereas he ſayth, <hi>He would haue thought it no robberie.</hi> It is as much as if he had ſayd, he did knowe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7789:19"/> that it was lawfull for him that we might knowe that hys ſubmiſſion was voluntarie, not of neceſſitie. Hitherto they haue tranſlated it in the Indicatiue moode, <hi>He thought,</hi> but the text requireth a Subiunctiue moode. And this is <hi>Paule</hi> his vſe to take the preterperfectence of the Indicatiue moode for the ſubiunctiue, vnderſtanding the potentiall adiection (as they call it.) So <hi>Rom. 9, 3.</hi> I did wiſh, for I would wiſh, and <hi>1. Cor. 2, 8.</hi> if they did knowe, for if they had knowne. There is no man that doth not ſée that <hi>Paule</hi> hetherto doth handle the glory of Chriſt, which belongeth to the amplify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his ſubmiſſion: he doth not therefore rehearſe what Chriſt did, but what it was lawfull for him to haue done. Furthermore, whoſoeuer doth not ſée his eternall diuinitie to be cléerely affirmed in theſe words, he is altogither blind. Neither doth <hi>Eraſmus</hi> deale ſhamefaſtly enough, who goeth about with his cauilles to make a ieſt as well of this place as of others like it. Indéede he confeſſeth euerie where, that Chriſt is God, but what doo his true confeſſion auaile me, if my faith be ſtrengthned by no authority of the Scripture. I confeſſe that <hi>Paule</hi> maketh no mention of the diuine eſſence of Chriſt, but therefore it followeth not that this place is not ſufficient to confute the impietie of the Arrians, who fained Chriſt to be a created God, and leſſe than the father: to be of the ſame ſubſtance with his father, they denied him: for where is there equalitie with God, without robberie, but in the only eſſence of God? for he remaineth alwaies the ſame God, who crieth by <hi>Eſay. 48, 11. I liue, and I will not giue my glory vnto another,</hi> the forme ſignifieth the figure, or the appearance as they ſpeake commonly, that alſo I confeſſe, but without God ſhall any ſuch forme be founde which is true and not counterfaite? As God therefore is knowne by his vertues, and his workes are teſtimonies of his eternall Godhead <hi>Rom. 1, 20.</hi> ſo the diuine eſſence of Chriſt is rightly proued by the maieſtie of Chriſt, which he had equall with his father, before he humbled himſelfe. Truely from me all the Diuels in hell can not wreſt thys
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7789:19"/> place, becauſe in God it is a ſtrong argument from his glory to his eſſence, which two things are inſeperable. <hi>He made him ſelfe of no reputation:</hi> This making of himſelfe of no reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is all one with his humilitie, whereof we ſhall ſée after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But this is ſpoken more emphatically, for he was brought vnto as nothing. Chriſt could not diſcharge himſelfe of his Diuinitie: but he kepte it hidden for a time, leaſte it ſhoulde appeare in the infirmitie of the fleſh. Therefore he laide away his glory, not by diminiſhing it, but by béeping it vnder in the ſight of men. But it is demanded whether he did that in reſpect as he was man: <hi>Eraſmus</hi> affirmeth it: but where was the forme of God before he was man? Therefore we muſt anſwere that <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of whole Chriſt, as he is God manifeſted in the fleſhe: yet this making himſelfe of no reputation agreeth not but only with his humanitie: As if I ſhoulde thus ſpeake of a man. A man, ſéeing he is mortal, is to be blockiſh, becauſe he thinketh on nothing but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: I vnderſtand the whole man, but I attribute mortalitie but vnto part of him that is to his body. Since therefore the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt is one, conſiſting of two natures: <hi>Paule</hi> ſaythe well, that he that was the ſonne of God, indéede equall wyth God, did notwithſtanding abſtaine from his glorie, when in the fleſh he carried the fourme of a ſeruant. It is ſecondly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded alſo, how he is ſaide to be of no reputation, who by his miracles and by his vertues proued himſelfe alwayes to be the ſonne of God, and in whome <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifieth <hi>1.14.</hi> that glory beſéeming the ſonne of God was alwaies to be ſéene: I anſwere that the humility of the fleſh, was notwithſtanding like a vaile wherewith his diuine maieſtie was couered: In which reſpect, he would neither haue his tranſfiguration pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſhed, vntill he were riſen againe, &amp; when he perceiueth the houre of death to be at hand, then he ſaith: <hi>Father glorifie thy ſonne. Iohn. 17.1.</hi> Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> alſo teacheth, <hi>Rom. 1.4.</hi> that he was declared the Sonne of God by his reſurrection. And againe, <hi>2. Cor. 13.4.</hi> He ſuffered throughe the infirmitie of the fleſh. Finally, the Image of God did ſo ſhine forth in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7789:20"/> Chriſt, that notwithſtanding he was caſt away in outward ſight, and in the opinion of men brought to nothing. For he did beare the forme of a ſeruant, and for that cauſe did he take vppon him our nature, that in it he might be the ſeruaunt of his father, yea euen the ſeruant of men. For <hi>Paule</hi> calleth him the miniſter of the Circumciſion. <hi>Rom. 15.8.</hi> and he himſelfe teſtifieth of him ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he came to miniſter. <hi>Mat. 20.28.</hi> &amp; long before, the ſame thing was foretold by <hi>Eſaie. 42.1. <hi>Behold my ſeruant,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>In the likenes of men.</hi> The gréek word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in this place is as much as placed: for <hi>Paule</hi> doth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie that he was brought into the order of men, that euen in his ſhape he might nothing differ from the common ſorte of men. The <hi>Marcionites</hi> haue abuſed this teſtimonie, to proue their fantaſticall ſpirit which they dreamed on: but they may eaſily be refuted, becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> diſputeth here of no other thing, but in what manner Chriſte behaued himſelfe, or in what condition he was buſied in the world. He that is a true man, ſhall notwithſtanding be thought vnlike to others, if he ſo behaue himſelfe as if he were exempt from the lawe of others. <hi>Paule</hi> denieth that this was in Chriſt, but that he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo, that he appeared vnto euery man to be of the number of men, and yet was he farre other than man, althoughe he were a true man. Therefore the <hi>Marcionites</hi> deale too chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhly, who from the like condition of men, draw their argu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment to deny the trueth of hys nature. <hi>He was found</hi> It ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth here, knowne or ſéene: for he handleth here his eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as was ſaide, that is (as before he affirmed, that in very déede he was God equall to the Father: ſo here he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth that he was accounted as an abiect, and as one of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſort of men: but we muſt alwayes repeate that whych he ſaid euen now, that ſuch ſubmiſſion was voluntary. <hi>9 <hi>He was made obedient.</hi>
                  </hi> This was great humilitie, that of a maiſter he made himſelfe a ſeruant: but he ſayth he went farther, that when he was not only immortall, but the Lorde of life and death, yet he obeyed his Father euen vnto the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of death: thys was hys loweſt abaſing of hymſelfe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeciallye
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7789:20"/> conſideryng the kinde of his death, whyche he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth forthwyth to exaggerate the matter more: for in ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng he was not only reprochfull before men, but alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed before GOD. Such is the example of his humilitye, that it ſhoulde euen ſwallowe vp the myndes of all men: It is ſo farre of that it can be expreſſed in wordes accordyng to the worthines thereof. <hi>9 <hi>Wherefore God hath exalted him on hygh.</hi>
                  </hi> By addyng a comforte, he teacheth that humilitye is carefully to bée deſired, whyche the witte of man doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre from. No man will denye, but that a iuſt thing is required of vs, when we are commanded to imitate Chriſt, but this reaſon moueth vs that we ſhoulde more willinglye imitate hym, when we heare that there is nothyng bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for vs, than to bée framed to hys Image. That they are bleſſed whoſoeuer are humbled wyllyngly with Chriſt, he proueth by his example: for from a moſt deſpiſed eſtate, he was exalted vnto the higheſt dignitie: whoſoeuer therefore humbleth himſelfe, ſhall likewiſe be exalted: he that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſubmiſſion nowe, how ſhall he come to the glory of the heauenlye kyngdome? This place haue giuen occaſion to the Sophiſters, or rather they themſelues haue taken occaſion that they ſaye that Chriſte firſte merited for hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and then for others. Firſt, althoughe they ſpake no vntrueth, yet ſuch profane cogitations muſte be auoyded, whych doe darken the grace of Chriſte, when we imagyne that he came for any other cauſe, than for our ſaluation: who doth not ſée that it is ſuggeſted by Sathan, that Chriſte ſuffered on the croſſe, to get vnto hymſelfe by the merit of his worke, that whiche he had not? For the holye ghoſte wyll haue vs in the death of Chryſte to beholde, to taſte, to repute, to féele, to acknowledge none other thing than the méere bountye of GOD and of Chriſte himſelfe only, and ſuche an ineſtimable loue towarde vs, that forgettyng hymſelfe, he beſtowed himſelfe and his life vppon vs. As ofte as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7789:21"/> the ſcripture ſpeaketh of the death of Chriſt, it ſetteth downe the fruite and price thereof to be in vs, becauſe by it we are redéemed, reconciled vnto God, reſtored vnto righteouſnes, clenſed from our filthines, life procured for vs, and the gate of life opened: who can therefore denye, that theſe men by the inſtinct of Sathan, declaime againſt it, ſaying that the eſpeciall fruite is in Chriſte hymſelfe that he had firſt regarde of hym ſelfe than of vs, that he deſerued glory, firſt for himſelfe before ſaluation for vs? Furthermore I deny that to be true which they affirme, &amp; I ſay they haue wickedly wreſted <hi>Paules</hi> wordes, to proue they lye, for that the Illatiue worde ſignifieth here rather a conſequence than a cauſe. It is euident hereby, becauſe otherwiſe it follow that man may merit diuine honour, and obtaine the very throne of God, which is not only abſurd, but horrible to be ſpoken: For what exaltation of Chriſt doth the Apoſtle here declare? namely that in him is fulfilled whatſoeuer God only challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to him ſelfe in <hi>Eſaie.</hi> Therefore the glory of God, and the maieſtie which is ſo proper vnto him, that it can be tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlated to none other, ſhall be the rewarde of mans workes. Beſides if they vrge the word in no reſpect of abſurditie, the anſwere is eaſie: he was ſo giuen vnto vs by his father, that al his life was appointed a glaſſe for vs to look in: therfore as a glaſſe although it hath brightnes, yet hath it not for itſelf, but to that end that the vſe and commoditie thereof ſhoulde be for others: ſo, neither hath Chriſte either gotten or taken any thing for himſelfe, but all for vs. For what newe exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation did he néede I pray, who was equall with his father? Let therefore the godly readers learne to abhore the Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall ſophiſters with their wreſted ſpeculations. <hi>He hath giuen him a name.</hi> The name is here taken for dignitie, which in all tongues is ſufficiently knowne: like a blocke he lyeth without name, that is without honour, eſpecially it is a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar ſpeaking in the ſcripture. It ſignifieth therefore that greateſt power is giuen vnto Chriſt, and that he is placed in the higheſt degrée of honour, that no dignitie, neither in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, nor in earth, can be found like vnto his: whereof it fol-
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:7789:21"/> ſhoweth that it is a diuine name, and that he alſo expoundeth, bringing in the words of <hi>Eſaie 45.23.</hi> where the prophet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of the worſhip of God to be ſpread abroade throughe out the whole world, bringeth in god ſpeaking after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. I liue, and all knées ſhall bowe vnto me, and all tongues ſhal ſweare vnto me. It is certaine that that worſhip is there noted which doth peculiarly belong vnto God. I know that ſome doe ſubtelly diſpute of the name of Ieſus, as thoughe it were deriued from the ineffable word <hi>Iehoua:</hi> but I find no ſubſtance in the reaſons they alleage, and I am not delighted with vaine ſubtelties, and it is dangerous to ieſt in ſo great a matter. Moreouer, who doth not ſée that the expoſition is ſtrained &amp; nothing proper, when <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of the whole maieſtie of Chriſt to reſtraine his ſentence vnto <hi>2.</hi> ſillables: as if a man would examine the ſyllables in the worde <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> to find the greatnes of the name that <hi>Alexander</hi> got to himſelfe: therefore their ſubteltie being ſo ſlender, is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gloſe farre from the meaning of <hi>Paule.</hi> But the Sorboni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſophiſters are more than ridiculous, which gather out of this preſent place, that the knée muſt bow ſo oft as the name Ieſus is pronounced, as thoughe it were a magicall worde, which had all the force incloſed in the ſound. But <hi>Paule</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the honour which is to be giuen to the ſonne of God, and not to ſyllables. <hi>Al knees ſhoulde bowe.</hi> Although men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner be reuerenced: yet it is not to be doubted that that worſhip is here noted, which is proper vnto god, a ſigne whereof is the bowing of the knée, wherein it is méete to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, that God is not only to be worſhipped with inwarde affection of the hart, but alſo with outward profeſſion, if wée will giue him that whiche is his owne. Therefore when he will ſet out his lawfull worſhippers, he ſayth they haue not bowed their knée before the Image of <hi>Baal, 2 Reg. 19.18.</hi> But here ariſeth a queſtion whether this doth belong to the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie or to the humanitie of Chriſt? for both of them are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, for vnto his diuinitie no newe thing coulde be giuen: with his humanitie either by it ſelfe, or ſeuerally great exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation agreeth not, that he ſhoulde be worſhihped as God: I
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7789:22"/> anſwere that this is ſpoken of the whole perſon of Chriſt, as many other things, in reſpect that he is God manifeſted in the fleſh: for neither did he humble himſelfe touching his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie only, or touching his godhead only: but becauſe he hauing put vpon him our fleſh, laye hid vnder the infirmitye thereof. So againe God hath exalted his ſonne in the ſame fleſh, wherein he liued as an abiect, and without honor in the world, vnto the higheſt degrée of honor, that he ſitteth at hys right hande. But <hi>Paule</hi> ſéemeth not to agrée with hymſelfe, who to the <hi>Rom. 14.11.</hi> citeth the ſame teſtimonie when he goeth about to proue that Chriſte ſhall once be the Iudge of the quicke and the deade: but it were not fit for that purpoſe, if it were already fulfilled as here he witneſſeth. I anſwere that it is ſo with the kingdome of Chriſte, that it increaſeth dayly, and is augmented to the better: but the perfection ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is not euident, nor ſhal be euident vntill the latter daye of Iudgement. So both is true, that all things are now ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vnto Chriſt, and yet this ſubiection ſhall not be abſolute before the day of the reſurrection, becauſe then that ſhall bée finiſhed, which now is but begun: therefore this prophecy not without cauſe, is diuerſly applied vnto diuers times, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things doe not define y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Chriſt in one mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of time, but doe deſcribe it in their whole courſe. But hereof we gather that Chriſte is that euerlaſting God that ſpeaketh by <hi>Eſaie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Of things in Heauen, and things in earth, and things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth.</hi>
                  </hi> When <hi>Paule</hi> from the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vnto them vnder the earth ſubmitteth all things vnto Chriſt: the papiſtes trifle very childiſhly in gatheryng Purgatorie out of his wordes. Their argument is after this ſort: it is ſo farre of, that the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels bowe theyr knées vnto Chriſt, that by all meanes they are rebels againſt him, and authors of rebellion vnto others (as though it were not written, that they doe tremble at the only mention of god.) <hi>Iames 2.19.</hi> What therfore when they ſhal come in preſence before the tribunal ſeat of Chriſt his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? truly I confes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wil neuer willingly, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ready obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be ſubiect: neyther doth <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeake here of voluntary
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7789:22"/> obedience, but rather we returne ſuch a conuerſion againſte themſelues: the fire of Purgatorie according to theyr owne ſaying is temporall, and ſhal be aboliſhed at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: therefore this place cannot be vnderſtoode of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> in another place denieth that this prophecy ſhall be accompliſhed, vntill Chriſt ſhall appeare vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Who doth not ſée that in theſe filthy quiddities they are twiſe children. <hi>11. <hi>Vnto the glory of God the father.</hi>
                  </hi> It might alſo be read <hi>in the glory</hi> becauſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is oft times vſed in the place of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Yet I had rather retaine the proper ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſenſe, that the maieſty of god as it was by Chriſt made manifeſt vnto men: ſo it ſhould ſhine againe in Chriſt, &amp; the father ſhoulde be glorified in the ſon. Looke <hi>Iohn 5</hi> and <hi>17.</hi> and you ſhal haue the expoſition of this place.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>12</hi>
                     </bibl> Wherefore my beloued, as ye haue alwaies obeyed, not as in my preſence only, but now much more in my abſence, worke out your owne ſaluation with feare and trembling.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>13</hi>
                     </bibl> For it is God that worketh in you both to will and to doe, of his good pleaſure,</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>14.</hi>
                     </bibl> Doe al things without murmurings and reaſonings.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>15</hi>
                     </bibl> That ye may be ſuch of whome no man can complaine, and the ſincere ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of god without rebuke in the mids of a naugh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty &amp; crooked generation, among whome, ſhine ye as lyghtes in the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>16</hi>
                     </bibl> Holding forth the word of life, vnto my glory, vntill the day of chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that I haue not run in vaine, neither labored in vain.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12. <hi>Wherefore.</hi>
                  </hi> He ſhutteth vp all that laſt exhortation with a generall ſentence, that they ſhould humble themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand of the Lord: for that will eaſily bring to paſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laying away al fiercenes they ſhal be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle &amp; curteous amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. This only is a fit reaſon whereby the wit of man may learne to waxe gentle, when by comparing with god, he ſearcheth into hymſelfe, who pleaſed hymſelfe ſeuerallye in hys owne deuiſes. <hi>As yee haue alwaies obeyed</hi> He prayſeth their former obedience, that he might the more encourage them to goe forwarde. But becauſe it is the property of hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites to approue themſelues to the eie, but when they are out
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7789:23"/> of ſight, to fauour them ſelues with more liberty, as it were the cauſe of their reuerence and feare béeyng remooued. He admoniſheth them that they would not only ſhewe themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues obedient to the eye, but alſo that they obey him being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that ſo much the more: for if he were preſente, he might prick them forward, and enforce them with daily ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions. Now therfore it is néedefull that while their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailour is away, they woulde be carefull for them ſelues <hi>with feare and trembling.</hi> In this he would haue the Philippians to teſtifie and approue their obedience, that they might be lowly and humble. This moreouer is the fountaine of humilitie to acknowledge how miſerable we are, and néedy of al goodnes vnto the which he calleth them in this ſentence: for whence commeth pride but from ſecuritie, which blinde confidence bringeth forth, whiles we pleaſe our ſelues, and are rather puffed vp with a confidence of our owne vertue, than ſtay vp on the grace of God? The contrary vnto vice is feare, to the which he exhorteth them: but although in the text exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be before doctrine: yet in order it is after, becauſe from thence it is drawne, I will therefore begin with doctrine. <hi>It is God that worketh in vs.</hi> This is the true engine to deſtroy all lofti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: this is the ſworde to kill all pride when we heare that we are nothing at all, and can doe nothing, but by the alone grace of God (I vnderſtand ſupernaturall grace) which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céedeth from the ſpirit of regeneration: For in as muche as we are men, in God we are, we liue and are moued: but here <hi>Paule</hi> rather diſputeth of another kinde of mouing, than of that vniuerſall. Let vs ſée now what he attributeth vnto god, what he leaueth vnto vs. There be two principally to be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered in doing any thing: The will, and the power of the effect: both of them he affirmeth for certainety to be in God, what more doth remaine for vs wherein we may boaſt? It is no doubt but this diuiſion is as much as if <hi>Paule</hi> had ſayde the whole in one word: for the will is the foundation, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is the outward ſhew of the building. And he hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a great deale more than if he had ſaide God were the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7789:23"/> of the beginning and ending. For then the Sophiſters might cauill that there were ſome middle thing left vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but now what ſhall they finde at all proper vnto vs? They ſweate much in their ſchooles, that they might reconcile frée will with the grace of god: I ſay ſuch a frée wil as they faine, which is both flexible by his proper motion, and hath a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and ſeuerall power, whereby it worketh with the grace of god. I doo not contend about the word: but the thing itſelfe. That therefore frée will maye agrée with grace, thus they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, that god truly doth repaire in vs his frée election, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are able to will that is good: ſo they acknowledge the abilitie to will that is good to come from God: but the good will it ſelfe they attribute vnto men: but <hi>Paule</hi> doth pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this (without exception) to be the worke of God: for he doth not ſay that our hartes only are bowed or ſtirred vp by God, or that the weakenes of our good will is helped: but that our good will is altogither made by God. Whereas they ſclander vs, that we make men like vnto ſtones, when we teache that they haue no goodnes but of méere grace, they doo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently, for we confeſſe that we haue a will by nature, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is euill by the corruption of ſin, then it beginneth to to be good when it is reformed by God. Neyther doo we ſaye that a man doo any good willinglye, but then when the will is ruled by the ſpirit of God. Therefore touchyng thys part, we ſée that the whole praiſe is giuen to God: and that it is friuolous which the Sophiſters teache, that grace is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto vs, and placed as it were in the middes, that wée may embrace it if we liſte. For except God ſhoulde worke ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually in vs, he coulde not be ſaide to worke a good wyll. Concernyng the ſecond part we muſt thinke the ſame thing. god, he ſayth, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is the worker whereby wée worke: therefore he bringeth vnto an end thoſe godly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whiche he hath inſpired into vs, leaſte they ſhoulde be in vaine, as he promiſeth by <hi>Ezechiell. 11.20. <hi>I will make them to walke in my preceptes,</hi>
                  </hi> wherby we gather, that perſeuerance alſo is his méere gift. <hi>Of his good pleaſure.</hi> Some doo interprete
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7789:24"/> this for good intent of the minde: but I rather refer it vnto God, and I vnderſtande it for his willing affection whyche commonly they call his good pleaſure. For in this ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo the vſe of the gréeke worde is more common, and the text doth require it. For this is <hi>Paules</hi> drift, to gyue all vnto God, and to take all from vs Therefore not being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to haue giuen vnto God the effecte, both of the good wyll and of the worke, he aſcribeth both vnto his frée mercy, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he excludeth the fayned opinion of the ſophiſters touching grace following, whiche they imagine to be the rewarde of merit. Therefore he teacheth that all the courſe of our life, if we liue aright, is directed by god, and that of his frée goodnes. <hi>With feare and trembling.</hi> Hereof <hi>Paule</hi> inferreth an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they ſhoulde worke out theyr ſaluation with feare: he ioyneth feare and trembling togither, for a ſerious and carefull feare, accordyng to his manner, to increaſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more. Therefore he ſhaketh off as well drouſines, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. By the word worke he chaſtiſeth ſlothfulnes, which is alwaies wittie to ſéeke a going forwarde: but it ſéemeth to haue a ſwéete ſmell in the grace of God, becauſe if GOD worketh in vs, why ſhoulde not we waxe ſlothfull? But the holy ghoſt admoniſheth vs that he will worke in liuelye In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments: but ſtraight way he beateth backe pryde, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending feare and trembling. We muſt alſo diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that which he inferreth: from God, he ſayth, you haue all thinges, therefore bée carefull and humble: for there is nothyng whyche ſhoulde more inſtructe vs vnto mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye and feare, than when we heare that we ſtande by the onlye grace of GOD, ready forthwyth to fall, if he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe hys hande but a lyttle. The confidence of our ſelues breedeth Securitye and fiercenes. Thys is expreſſed: who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer truſte vnto theyr owne ſtrength, they waxe inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lente through pryde, and ſleepe in Securitye. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medye therefore agaynſte both theſe euills is, if diſtruſting our ſelues we depende all togither vppon God only. And verilye that man hath trulye profited as well in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7789:24"/> of the grace of god, as of his own infirmitie, who being wakened from ſecuritie, earneſtly requireth helpe of god: but they that are puffed vp with a truſte of their owne ſtrength it is neceſſary that they ſhoulde become drunken in ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Wherefore the ſclander, wherewith the Papiſts burden vs, is impudent, namelye, that by extollyng the grace of God, and by beatyng downe free wyl, we make men ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, we ſhake off the feare of God, and take away all care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes. But the Readers doe ſee that <hi>Paule</hi> here doth not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter of exhortation from the doctrine of the Papiſtes: but from our doctrine. <hi>God, he ſayth, doth all thynges in you.</hi> Therefore ſubmytte your ſelues vnto hym with feare. Truly, I doe not denye but many men hearyng that there is no goodnes in vs, wyll wyth more libertye flatter them ſelues in theyr faultes. But I denye that this is the faulte of the doctrine whyche being receyued as it ought bringeth forth a carefulnes in our hartes. Moreouer the Papiſts abuſe thys place to ouerthrowe the certaynetye of Fayth: for he that trembleth, is vncertayne. Thus therefore they take <hi>Paule</hi> hys wordes, as though in all our life we ſhould ſtacker in the truſt of our ſaluation: but if we wyll confer <hi>Paule</hi> with himſelfe, he doth not here exhorte vs vnto doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng, becauſe euerye where he commendeth confidence and a full aſſurance of God hys mercyes: but the Solution is eaſie, if any man ſeeke the true ſence without contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. There are two kyndes of feare: the one engendreth carefulnes wyth humility: the other doubtyng. The firſte is oppoſed as well to the ſecurity and ſlothfulnes of the fleſh, as vnto pride: the other is oppoſed vnto the certainetye of faith. Moreouer we muſt marke, that as the faythful doo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely reſt vpon the grace of God, ſo whiles they caſt backe their eyes vnto their owne frailety, they doe not ſleepe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely: but for feare of daunger, ſtirre vp themſelues vnto praiers: notwithſtanding it is ſo far of, that this feare ſhould trouble the quiet ſtate of their conſtancie, and ſhake their faith, that it rather co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for the diſtruſt of our ſelues
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7789:25"/> maketh vs reſt more ſtrongly vpon the mercy of God, and to that ende tende <hi>Paules</hi> wordes: for he requireth nothing of the Philippians, but that they ſhould ſubmit themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god, with a true denying of themſelues. <hi>Worke out your own ſaluation.</hi> As the <hi>Pelagians</hi> in old time: ſo the papiſtes at this day doo proudely boaſte of this place, to extoll the vertue of man: for whiles the former ſentence is obiected vnto them: <hi>It is GOD that worketh:</hi> they ſtraight way beate it backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine (as it were with this buckler.) <hi>Woorke out your owne Saluation.</hi> Since therefore the worke is giuen in common both vnto god and vnto man, they attribute halfe vnto either. In ſumme, from the word <hi>worke</hi> they gather frée will, &amp; from the word <hi>ſaluation,</hi> they gather meate of eternall life. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaluation is taken for the whole courſe of our voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; vnder this word are comprehended al things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God doth accompliſh that perfection, vnto the whiche he hath appointed vs in his frée election. No man except he bée obſtinate and impudent will deny this: we are ſayde to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it, when being gouerned by the holy ghoſte, we attayne vnto a bleſſed life. It is God which calleth, who offreth ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. It is our dutie by faith to embrace that which he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and by our obedience to anſwere to his calling: but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe can we haue from our ſelues. Then therfore doo we any thing, when he hath prepared vs to doo it? The word which he vſeth ſignifieth properly to finiſh: but wée muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that which I ſaide, that <hi>Paule</hi> doth not diſpute how farre our ability doth extend, but doth teach ſimply, that god doth ſo worke in vs, that yet he ſuffereth vs not to waxe ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but exerciſeth vs being ſtrongly driuen forward by hys ſecrete motion. <hi>14. <hi>without murmurings.</hi>
                  </hi> Theſe are the fruites of that humility vnto the which he exhorted. For whoſoeuer attributing nothing to himſelfe, hath learned to ſubmit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe carefully vnto God, he will behaue himſelfe alſo quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among men. For where euery man pleaſe himſelfe there raigneth two vices: that one ſpeake againſt another, and that they ſtriue among themſelues by contention. Firſt therfore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7789:25"/> he forbiddeth maliciouſnes &amp; ſecrete grudgings: Then open contentions. He addeth alſo a third thing that they ſhoulde not giue others occaſion of complaining, whiche is wont to procéede of too much teſtines. Hatred is not alwaies to be fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, but we muſt indeauour that by our owne fault we make not our ſelues odious, that it may be fulfilled in vs, They ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me without a cauſe. <hi>Pſal. 35.19.</hi> Although if any woulde extende it further, I am not againſte him: for thence come murmurings &amp; diſputings, whileſt euery man beyond mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure caring for himſelfe, giueth vnto others occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine: yea this word may be taken actiuely, that it may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie not troubleſome men, nor complainers. And this ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication agreeth not ill with the text, becauſe the ſéede of all brawlings and backbitings, for the moſt part is complaining He ioyneth <hi>Sinoere,</hi> becauſe ſuch filthines will neuer come forth from purged minds. <hi>The ſonnes of God without reprehenſion</hi> It muſt thus be reſolued, without reprehenſion: becauſe yée are the ſonnes of God: for the adoption of GOD muſte bée the cauſe of a blameleſſe life, that by ſome ſimilitude we may reſemble our father. Although there was neuer ſuch perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, that nothing ſhoulde be found worthy repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: yet they are called irreprehenſible, who with al their care ſtriue to come thither, as it is ſaide in another place. <hi>In the mids of a peruerſe generation.</hi> The faithfull liue in the earth mingled with the vngodly, they drawe togither the common ayer, they enioy the common lande. And at that tyme alſo they were more diſperſed, becauſe there could ſcarce be found one godly houſe, which was not euery way compaſſed wyth vnbeléeuers. So much the more <hi>Paule</hi> pricketh forwarde the Philippians, that they ſhoulde carefully take héede to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all corruptions. The ſenſe is therefore: you are incloſed among the wicked: but in the meane while remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that by the adoption of God you are ſeparated from them. Therfore let there be euident ſignes in your life, which may make you differ. Moreouer, this reaſon muſt more prouoke you vnto a care of a godly and holy life: leaſt being entangled
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7789:26"/> by theyr vyces and contagion, you bée parte alſo of a croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation. Whereas he calleth the vnbeléeuers <hi>A peruerſe and crooked generation.</hi> That belongeth vnto the circumſtance of the place: for he warneth them, that they ſhoulde ſo muche the more diligentlye take héede, becauſe many offences woulde be thruſte in by the vnfaithful, which myghte hinder theyr right courſe: and the whole lyfe of the vnfaithfull woulde bée as a Laborinthe of diuerſe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, which woulde leade vs out of the waye: yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe they are <hi>Epithetes</hi> which agrée with the vnbelée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of all nations, and of all tymes. For if the harte of man be peruerſe and vnſearcheable, what ſhall bée the fruites of ſuche a roote? We are taughte therefore in theſe wordes, that there is nothyng pure in the life of man, vntill he be reformed by the Spirite of GOD. <hi>Among whome ſhine yee.</hi> The termination of the Gréeke verbe is doubtfull: for it might bée reade in the Indicatiue moode: <hi>Yee ſhine.</hi> But the Imperatiue moode better agreeth with the the exhortation He wil haue the faithful like lampes, which doe ſhine in the darkenes of the worlde. As if he ſhoulde ſaye, the vnfaithfull are the children of the nyghte, and in the worlde there is nothing but darkenes: but GOD hath illuminated you vnto this ende, that the purenes of your life might ſhine in thys darknes, whereby his grace might appeare moſte euident. So it is alſo ſaide by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <hi>The Lorde ſhall ariſe vppon thee, and his glory ſhall bee ſeene in thee. <hi>Eſaie. 60.2.</hi>
                  </hi> By and by it followeth. The gentiles ſhall walke in the light, and Kinges in the brightnes of thy countenance. Although <hi>Eſaie</hi> there preacheth rather of doctrine. And <hi>Paule</hi> here of the example of life (In reſpecte alſo of doctrine) Chriſte calleth his Apoſtles peculiarlye in another place, the light of the worlde. <hi>Math. 5.14.16. <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth the worde of life.</hi>
                  </hi> The reaſon why they ſhoulde bée lightes, is becauſe they beare the word of life, whereby they are lightned, that they alſo may ſhine vnto others. He allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto candels, wherein are ſet wéekes to burne, and he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7789:26"/> maketh vs like vnto the candels. He compareth the word of God vnto the wéeke of the candle, whence the light is. If you had rather haue another ſimilitude: we are the candleſticks, the doctrine of Chriſt is the candle, which being ſet in vs gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth light round about: And it ſignifie that we offer iniurie vnto the word of God, except it ſhine in vs by the purenes of our life. Hither appertaineth the ſaying of Chriſte: No man lighteth a candle and putteth it vnder a buſhell, &amp;c. <hi>Mat. 5.15</hi> So we are ſaide to beare the worde, that in the meane whyle we are borne by it, becauſe we are founded in it. But the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of bearing which <hi>Paule</hi> here handleth is this: that god vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this condition hath committed his doctrine vnto vs, not that we ſhoulde kéepe the lighte thereof ſuppreſſed and idle, but that we ſhoulde bring it forth vnto others. The ſumme is this, whoſoeuer are illuminated by the heauenly doctrine, do beare about that doctrine which may bewray and vncouer their ſhame, except they walke holily &amp; purely: but this light is therfore kindled, that they themſelues ſhoulde not only bee directed in the right way, but that they ſhoulde alſo ſhewe it forth vnto others. <hi>Vnto my glory.</hi> To increaſe their courage, he witneſſeth that which ſhal be glorious vnto him, if he haue not labored in vaine among them: not becauſe they doe loſe the price and the rewarde of their trauell, who haue labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red faithfully, yet without effect: but ſince the ſucceſſe of our miniſtery is the ſingular bleſſing of God, let vs not maruell if God alſo crowne that among his other gifts. As therefore ſo many churches gotten by <hi>Paule</hi> vnto Chriſt, doo now make his Apoſtleſhip honorable: ſo it is no doubte, but theſe victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhall haue place in the kingdome of Chriſte, as he ſaith a little after, you are my crowne. And it is no doubte but the triumph ſhal be ſo much the more excellent, as the déeds ſhal be more glorious. If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would aſke how <hi>Paule</hi> doo now reioyce in his labors, who in the <hi>2. Cor. 11.11.</hi> forbiddeth to reioyce in any thing but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord: the anſwere is eaſy, when as we haue caſte downe our ſelues &amp; al thinges that are ours before the Lord, and haue repoſed our whole glory in Chriſt:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7789:27"/> It is lawful alſo through Chriſt to reioice in the benefites of god, as it appeareth in the firſt epiſtle to the Corinthians: this parte <hi>Vntill the day of the Lord</hi> is a prick vnto the Philippians, for to perſeuer, ſince that the tribunall ſeat of Chriſte is ſet before them, from whence they muſt looke for the rewarde of theyr faith.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </bibl> And though I be offered vp vpon the ſacrifice and ſeruice of your faith, I reioyce, and reioyce with you all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </bibl> For the ſame cauſe alſo reioyce yee, and reioyce togyther with me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </bibl> And I hope in the Lorde that I ſhall alſo ſende Timotheus vnto you ſhortly, that I alſo may be quiet when I knowe your estate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </bibl> For I haue no man like minded, who will faithfully care for your matters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </bibl> For all ſeeke theyr owne, and not the things whiche are Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>22</hi>
                     </bibl> But ye knowe the proofe of him, that as a ſonne with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he hath ſerued with me in the goſpel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>23.</hi>
                     </bibl> Him therefore I hope to ſende, aſſoone as I knowe howe it will go with me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>24</hi>
                     </bibl> And I truſte in the Lorde that I alſo my ſelfe ſhall come ſhortly.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17 <hi>If I be offered.</hi>
                  </hi> In gréeke it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Wherefore he ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnto me to allude vnto thoſe ſacrifices, by the killing whereof, among the men of old time couenants &amp; bargaines were ratified: for the gréekes properly cal <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſacrifice of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to confirme a couenant. After this ſorte he calleth his death a confirmation of their faith, as certainely it ſhould be. But that the whole place might be more cléere, he ſayth that he ſacrificed vnto god, when he conſecrated them through the goſpel. The like ſaying is to the <hi>Romanes. 15.16.</hi> for there he he bringeth in himſelfe as a prieſt, which offreth the gentiles vnto God through the goſpell. And as the goſpell is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſword to kill ſacrifices, ſo faith is as it were the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: for there is no faith without mortification, by the which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7789:27"/> wée are conſecrated vnto God. He putteth two words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſacrifice and ſeruice, whereof the former is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the Philippians, who were offred vnto God: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto <hi>Paule:</hi> for he is the act of the ſacrifice. It is as much as adminiſtration and ſo it comprehendeth the functions and duties of eyther kindes: but here it belongeth properly vnto the worſhip of God, as the Latines ſay, <hi>operari ſacris,</hi> to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Now <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith that he ſhall be ioyfull if he ſhoulde bée offered vpon ſuch a ſacrifice, that it might be more ratified &amp; ſtrong. This is to teach the goſpell from the harte, when wée are ready to confirme with our owne bloud that whyche wée teache. Beſides, here is a profitable doctrine to be gathered touching the nature of faith: namely, that it is not a vaine thing: but ſuch a thing as conſecrateth a man vnto God: and alſo the miniſters of the goſpell haue here an excellent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, who are ſaide to be the prieſtes of God, to offer ſacrifices vnto him: for with what earneſtnes woulde he bende him ſelfe to be carefull in preaching, which knoweth that this is a ſacrifice acceptable vnto God? Touching this kinde of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whileſt the miſerable papiſts know nothing, they feigne another kinde which is extreame ſacrilege. He ſaith, <hi>I reioice togither with you:</hi> that if it ſhoulde happen that he ſhould dye, they might knowe it ſhoulde be for their profite, and they might reape fruite by his death. <hi>18. <hi>Reioyce yee.</hi>
                  </hi> By this chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes he animateth the Philippians, and enflameth them to ſuffer death valiantly, in which the faithful ſuffer no euyl. For before he taught that death ſhoulde be to him aduantage, yet here he eſpecially bewareth that his death trouble not the Philippians. Therefore he denieth that it ſhall bée any cauſe of ſorrowe: yea they muſte rather reioyce, becauſe they ſhould finde it fruiteful: for although of it ſelfe it were a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous loſſe to be depriued of ſuch a teacher, yet the recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhould not be lighter, becauſe the goſpell ſhoulde bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by his bloud. In the meane while he admoniſheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that death priuately to himſelfe ſhall be ioyful, whereas <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi> tranſlateth it in the preſent tenſe, <hi>You doe reioyce.</hi> It is
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7789:28"/> altogither farre off. <hi>19. <hi>And I hope.</hi>
                  </hi> He promiſeth vnto them the comming of <hi>Timotheus,</hi> that by looking for him, they might ſtay themſelues more manfully, and not yéelde to the deceiuers: for as in warre the hope of ſuccor kéepeth ſtill the mindes of ſoldiers that they faint not: ſo this cogitation alſo might giue muche courage vnto the Philippians. He ſhall come ſhortly that ſhall oppoſe himſelfe againſte the attempts of our enimies, and if the only expectation of him did ſo much preuaile, his preſence ſhould be much more forcible. The con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition is to be noted, wherein he ſubmitteth himſelfe to the prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, determining nothing without y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: as truly it is lawful to appoint nothing for the time to come, but vnder the hand of God the Lord (as I may ſo ſay) Where he addeth <hi>That I alſo may be quiet,</hi> he declareth his loue towards them (as much to ſay) as he was ſo careful for their da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, that except he knew their proſperous eſtate, he could not be well. <hi>20 <hi>I haue no man like minded.</hi>
                  </hi> Althoughe manye gather a diuerſe ſenſe, I thus interpret it, I haue no man ſo well minded to be careful for your matters: for in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Paule</hi> rather compareth <hi>Timotheus</hi> with others, than with him ſelfe: and truly for that purpoſe he giueth him a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular praiſe, that for his rarenes he might be in greater eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. <hi>21. <hi>For all men ſeeke their owne.</hi>
                  </hi> He ſpeaketh not of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who had altogither caſt away the care of godlines, but of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome he accounted for brethren, yea whome he ſuffered in his owne company: yet he ſaith that they are ſo cunning in caring for their owne matters, that they are more cold in the work of the Lord. In ſhew it ſéemeth to be no grieuous fault to ſéeke ones owne: but how intollerable it is in the ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of Chriſt it appeareth thereof, that it maketh them altogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnprofitable, whome it poſſeſſeth: for it cannot be that he ſhould employ him ſelfe for the Churche, that is addicted vnto himſelfe. Therefore thou wilt ſaye: dyd <hi>Paule</hi> che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſhe wyth himſelfe men of no goodnes and diſſemblers? I aunſwere that it is not ſo to bée taken, as thoughe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing altogyther bent to theyr owne profitte, they had no
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7789:28"/> care at all of the Churche: but becauſe they being entangled with theyr owne priuate commodities, they were more negligent to promote the publique benefite of the Churche: for it is neceſſarye that one of theſe affections muſte raygne in vs: that eyther neglecting our ſelues, we ſhoulde bée carryed vnto Chriſte, and vnto thoſe thynges that are Chryſtes: or elſe béeyng too muche addicted to our owne profit, we ſhoulde ſerue Chryſt for faſhion ſake. Hereof ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth how great an hinderance it is vnto the miniſters of the Churche, to ſéeke theyr owne. Neyther are theſe excuſes of any force: I am iniurious to no man, I muſte haue regarde of my ſelfe: I am not ſo harde harted: but I am carefullye mooued with reſpecte of mine owne commoditie: for thou muſte departe from thine owne right, that thou mayeſt performe thy dutie: thy reaſon is neither to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before the glory of Chriſte, nor to be made equal with it: whether ſoeuer Chriſte calleth thee, thou muſt goe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, leauing all other thinges. So thou muſte looke backe vnto thy vocation, that thou muſte turne awaye thy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from all thinges that may call thee backeward. Thou maieſt liue in another place more wealthily: but God hath bounde thee to a Churche whiche mainetaine thée but ſclen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly. In another place there is more honour: but God hath giuen thée that place, in which thou muſt liue humbly. In an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place the aire is more healthfull, or the countrye more pleaſant: but here thy ſtanding is appoynted. Thou wouldſt wiſh that thou hadſt rather to doo with a more gentle people: either their vnthankfulnes, or their fiercenes, or their pryde offendeth thée. Finally thou doſt not agree with the wit &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try: yet thou muſt ſtriue with thy ſelfe, &amp; after a ſort offer viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary deſires, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou maiſt increaſe that good which thou haſt gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for thou art not frée, or at thy own liberty. To conclude thou muſt forget thy ſelfe, if thou wilt ſerue GOD. And if <hi>Paule</hi> doth reproue them ſo ſeuerely, who had greater care of them ſelues than of the Churche, what iudgemente doe they looke for, who bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng altogither carryed awaye by their owne buſines, doe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7789:29"/> nothing eſtéeme the edifyng of the Church? althoughe they now flatter themſelues: yet God will not ſpare them. So farre it is to be granted to the miniſters of the Churche, to ſeeke their owne, that they be not hindred from ſéekyng the kingdome of Chriſte: but by this meane they ſhall not nowe be ſaide to ſéeke their owne, becauſe the life of man is eſtéemed, according vnto the ſpeciall marke whereat it ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. Whereas he ſaith, <hi>All:</hi> you muſt not vrge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vniuerſal ſigne, that you admit no exception: for there were others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> but a very fewe: but he attributeth that vnto all, which was euery where common When wée heare <hi>Paule</hi> complaining in that golden age, wherein all vertues flouriſhed that true harted brethren were ſo hard to finde: let not vs diſcourage our ſelues, if at this day our eſtate be alike: only let euery man take héed to himſelfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be not worthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly numbred in this catalog. I woulde the Papiſts would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere me, where <hi>Peter</hi> was at that time, who ought to haue béene at <hi>Rome</hi> (if they ſay truth. Oh heauy and ſhameful diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe which <hi>Paule</hi> ſhould giue him: they fable therfore when they feigne that he was then Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Marke that the edifiyng of the Church is called the thinges of Chriſt, becauſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truly we doe his buſines, when we labor in trimming his vineyard. <hi>But yee knowe the experience of him.</hi> According to the word it is, you knowe the proofe of him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept you had rather haue it in the Imperatiue moode <hi>know yee.</hi> (for they coulde ſcarce take any triall of him in the time) but there is little matter of waight in that. This is eſpecially to be marked, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he giueth teſtimony vnto <hi>Timothie</hi> of his fayth and modeſtie. It appertaineth to his faith, in that he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that he ſerued with him in the goſpel, &amp; it is a ſigne of his modeſty, that he ſubmitted himſelfe to him, as vnto his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That <hi>Paule</hi> commendeth this vertue namely, it is no maruell, for it hath bene rare in all ages. At this daye what young man can be founde, who will yelde euen a little vnto his elders? ſuch inſolencie ſpringeth and boyleth forth in that age. In this place (as in many other) we ſée what an earneſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7789:29"/> care <hi>Paule</hi> hath to beautifie godly miniſters, not ſo much for their cauſe, as that it belongeth to the whole Churche, that ſuch ſhould be loued and reuerenced, and be in great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. <hi>And I truſte L my ſelfe.</hi> This alſo he addeth, leaſte they ſhoulde thinke that anye thing had happened, which might change the purpoſe of hys comming, whereof before he had made mention: yet alwaies he ſpeaketh with a condition. If it pleaſe the Lord: for although he hoped of deliuerance from the Lorde: becauſe we ſaid, there was no certaine promiſe that his hope was firmely ſetled, but hanging as it were vpon the ſecret counſell of God.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>25</hi>
                     </bibl> But I haue thought it neceſſary to ſende vnto you Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus my brother and companion in laboure, and fellow ſoldier: but your Apostle, and the minister of my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>26</hi>
                     </bibl> Becauſe he longed after you all, and was ful of heauineſſe, becauſe yee had heard that he had beene ſicke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>27</hi>
                     </bibl> And truly he was ſicke, very neere vnto death: but god had mercy on him, &amp; not on him only, but on me alſo, that I ſhould not haue ſorrow vpon ſorrow.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>28</hi>
                     </bibl> I ſente hym therefore the more diligently, that when yee ſee him, yee myght agayne reioyce, and I might be the leſſe ſorrowfull</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>29</hi>
                     </bibl> Receyue him therefore in the Lorde with all gladnes, and make much of ſuch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>30</hi>
                     </bibl> Becauſe that for the worke of Chriſte, he was neere vnto death, offeryng his life vnto danger, that he might fulfill that ſeruice which was wanting on your parte towarde me.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>25 Epaphroditus.</hi> After he had comforted them by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing his owne comming, and the comming of <hi>Timotheus,</hi> preſently alſo he ſtrengthneth them, ſending <hi>Ehaphroditus</hi> afore: leaſt in the meane time while he were certaine what would become of himſelfe (for this was the cauſe of his tary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) they ſhould want their paſtor, who might defende theyr well ordered eſtate. He commendeth <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> by many
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7789:30"/> names: that he is a brother, and an helper in the buſines of the Goſpell: that he is his fellow ſoldier: by which worde he expreſſeth what the condition of the miniſters of the goſpell is: namely that they muſt be in continuall warfare: for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than wil not ſuffer them to promote the goſpel without figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Therefore let them knowe who prepare them ſelues to edifie the Church, that there is warre proclaimed and readye againſt them. This truly is common vnto all Chriſtians to ſerue as ſoldiers in the tents of Chriſt, becauſe Sathan is the enimy of vs al: but eſpecially it appertaineth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſters of the word, who leade the armies, and carry the ſtandarde: yet more properly, it was lawfull for <hi>Paule</hi> to boaſt of hys warfare, who was exerciſed in all kind of battels, yea euen miraculouſly. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> commendeth <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> becauſe he was partaker with him of his ſtriuings: the name of Apoſtle is here generally (as in many other places) taken for euery Euangeliſt: except any had rather take it for a meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger ſent from the Philippians, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe two may ioyntlye be read togither: a meſſenger ſent to miniſter vnto <hi>Paule,</hi> but the former ſenſe in my iudgement agreeth better. He putteth this alſo among his praiſes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he miniſtred vnto him in priſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: of which thing we ſhal ſpeak more amply afterward. <hi>26. <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged after you.</hi>
                  </hi> A ſigne of a true paſtor, that when he was far of, &amp; willingly witholden from his godly dutie: yet he was mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with care and deſire of his flocke, and when he vnderſtood that his ſhéepe were ſad for his ſake, he was heauye for their griefe. In like maner the godly care of the Philippians for their paſtor is declared. <hi>27. <hi>But God had mercy on him.</hi>
                  </hi> He ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the grieuouſnes of the diſeaſe, becauſe <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> was ſicke without hope of life, that the goodnes of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring his helth might appeare more euidently. But it is a maruel that the Apoſtle doth account the prolonging of <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phroditus</hi> his life, in the number of Gods mercies: when be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he teſtified that he rather deſired death. And what is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for vs, than being deliuered out of ſo many miſeries of the world, to paſſe into the kingdome of god: eſpecially being
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7789:30"/> deliuered from the bondage of ſinne, in the which he cryeth out. <hi>Rom. 7.24.</hi> that he was miſerable to enioy more fully the liberty of the ſpirit, whereby we may cleaue faſt vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of God? It were a long thing to recken vp all things, which cauſe that death is better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life vnto the faithfull, and more to be wiſhed for Therefore what mercy is that of god, when it doth nothing but prolong our miſeries? I anſwere that al things make not, but theſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this life eſtéemed in it ſelf, is an excellent benefit of God: eſpecially they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> liue vnto Chriſt are here happily exerciſed vnto the hope of heauenly glorye: and therefore we ſawe a little before, that life was to them aduantage. Furthermore there is another thing to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that GOD vouchſafeth vs no ſmal thing, when he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifieth him ſelfe in vs: for we muſt not ſo muche reſpect our life, as the ende wherefore we doe liue. <hi>And of me alſo that I ſhoulde not haue ſorrowe vpon ſorrowe. <hi>Paule</hi>
                  </hi> confeſſeth that the death of <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> would haue bene bitter vnto him, and herein he acknowledgeth that God ſpared him, in that he was againe reſtored vnto his health. Therfore he boſteth not of the ſenſeleſſenes of the Stoickes, as though he were made of iron, and frée from the affection of men. What therefore, ſome will ſay: where is the vnconquered courage of his minde? where is hys vnwearyed conſtancie? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that Chriſtian patience doe dyffer farre from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſenes of Philoſophers: muche more from that crooked and cruell hardenes of the Stoickes: for what vertue were it patiently to beare the croſſe, if there were no féeling of griefe and of bitternes in it? but whileſt the comfort of God doth ouercome this féeling, that we reſiſt not but rather wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly giue our backes to be beaten, then wée offer a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our obedience acceptable vnto GOD. So <hi>Paule</hi> confeſſeth that he did feele ſome ſorrowe and griefe in his bandes, notwythſtandyng he dyd ioyfullye ſuffer thoſe bands for Chriſt. He confeſſeth that he ſhould grieuouſly haue taken the death of <hi>Epaphroditus:</hi> yet at lengthe he would haue framed his affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the wil of god: although
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7789:31"/> al the hardenes of the matter is not yet wholly anſwered: for then we proue our obedience, when we bridle our naughtye affections, and giue not place to the infirmitie of the fleſhe. Two things therfore are to be conſidered, firſt that the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which god at the beginning put into our nature, are not euil of themſelues, becauſe they procéed not from the viciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our corrupted nature, but flow from god, who is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of them, of which ſort is ſorrow, which is taken for the death of our friends. Againe there were many other cauſes why <hi>Paule</hi> ſhould lament the death of <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi> &amp; thoſe not only blameleſſe, but altogither neceſſary. This firſt of al is a continuall thing with the faithfull, that in the death of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they are admoniſhed of the wrath of God againſte ſinne: but <hi>Paule</hi> was more moued with the loſſe of the church which he ſawe ſhoulde be deſtitute of an excellent paſtor, in ſo great a ſcarſitie of good men. They that would haue ſuch affections altogither taken away and extinguiſhed, doe not only feigne men as ſenceleſſe as ſtones, but cruell and hardharted. But in this corruption of nature, all things are ſo peruerſe in vs, that whatſoeuer our minds be moued to, they alwaies excéed meaſure. Hereof it commeth, that nothing of it ſelfe is ſo pure and right, which draweth not vnto it ſome contagion. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> (as he was a man) ſuffered ſomwhat in his grief beſéeming the nature of man. I deny not, for both he labored vnder his infirmitie, and alſo it was neceſſary that he ſhould be tempted, that by ſtriuing and reſiſting he might haue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ouercome. <hi>28. <hi>I haue ſent him more diligently.</hi>
                  </hi> The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> was no ſmall comfort vnto him: yet he ſo much preferred the ſaluation of the Philippians before his owne commodity, that he ſaith he reioiceth for his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, becauſe he was ſorrowfull by his owne occaſion to bée drawne from the flocke committed vnto him, and from the duties of him, though pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which he inioyed with the loſſe of them. Therefore he ſayth, that he ſhal be more glad for the ioy of the Philippians. <hi>29. <hi>Receiue him with all ioy.</hi>
                  </hi> He taketh all ioy for ſincere and ſurpaſſing ioy. And againe he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7789:31"/> him to the <hi>Philippians:</hi> he laboreth altogether in this point, that they ſhould be much eſtéemed, that prooue themſelues good and faithful paſtors. Neither doth he ſpeake only of one, but he commaundeth all ſuch to be had in eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, for they are precious ſtones taken out of the treaſure of God, and the rarer they are, the more worthier they are of greater value. And it is without doubt that God oftentimes doth puniſh our ingratitude, and our diſdainefull lothing of his word, by depriuing vs of good paſtors, whileſt he ſeeth all good men for the moſt part which he giueth vs, to be deſpiſed. He therefore that deſireth to haue the Church defended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the lying in waite, and the aſſaults of wolues: let him by the example of <hi>Paule</hi> haue care, that the authority of good paſtors may be eſtabliſhed, as contrarywiſe, the inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the diuell labour in nothing more than to ouerthrowe it by all meanes poſſible. <hi>Becauſe for the worke of Chriſt.</hi> I refer it vnto that infirmitie which he had gotten by his continuall diligence, therefore he reckoneth the diſeaſe of <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> among his vertues, as truely it was an euident ſigne of his feruent zeale. It is no vertue to be ſicke, but this is a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that thou ſerue Chriſt, not to ſpare thy ſelfe. <hi>Epaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> did perceiue that it would be dangerous for his health, if beyond meaſure he were inſtant vpon him, yet he had rather neglect his health, than to be behind in his dutie. And that he might the more commend this déede vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> he ſayth, it was a ſupplying of their wants, becauſe they bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing farre aſunder, could not beſtowe their trauell vppon <hi>Paule</hi> béeing at <hi>Rome.</hi> Therefore <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> being ſent for this purpoſe, did fulfill their dutie. He calleth the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience vnto himſelfe the worke of the Lorde, as truely there is nothing wherein we can better beſtowe our trauell vpon God, than whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt we ſuccour his ſeruaunts béeing diſtreſſed for the truth of the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:7789:32"/>
               <head>Chapter. 3.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oreouer my brethren reioyce in the Lord. It greeueth me not to write the ſame things vnto you, and for you it is a ſure thing.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2</hi>
                        </bibl> Beware of dogs, beware of euill laborers, beware of conciſion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>3</hi>
                        </bibl> For we are the circumciſion which worſhip God in ſpirit, and reioyce in Chriſt Ieſus, and haue no confidence in the fleſh.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>4</hi>
                        </bibl> Although I alſo haue confidence in the fleſh: if any other man thinketh, he hath whereof he might truſt in the fleſhe, more I.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>5</hi>
                        </bibl> Circumciſed the eight day, of the kindred of Iſraell, of the tribe of Beniamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrewes, according to the lawe a Phariſee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>6</hi>
                        </bibl> Concerning zeale I perſecuted the Church: touching righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes which is in the lawe I was vnrebukeable.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eioyce in the Lord.</hi> This is a concluſion of the things that went before: for becauſe Satan did not ceaſe to buffet them with dayly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, he biddeth them be ſecure and of a good courage. By this reaſon he exhorteth them vnto conſtancie, leaſt they ſhould fall away from the doctrine which they had once receiued. And the word <hi>Moreouer</hi> doth note a continuall tenor, leaſt thorough many hinderances they ſhould ceaſe to extend their holy ioy. It is a rare vertue when Satan goeth about to prouoke vs thorough the bitternes of the croſſe, that the name of God might be vnpleaſant vnto vs, to reſt in the only taſte of God his grace, that all our troubles, gréeues, cares, and ſorrowes might be made ſwéete. <hi>To write the ſame things vnto you</hi> Héere he beginneth to ſpeake of the falſe Apoſtles, with whome notwithſtanding he fighteth not hand to hand, as in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> but in a few words he bitterly refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them as much as was ſufficient: for becauſe they had only tempted the <hi>Philippians,</hi> and had not vanquiſhed them,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7789:32"/> a iuſt diſputation was not ſo neceſſary to refute their errors, wherevnto they had neuer yéelded their eares. Simply ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he admoniſheth them, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould be diligent and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue in diſcerning &amp; auoiding of deceiuers. Firſt, he calleth them <hi>dogs,</hi> by a metaphore taken from hence, becauſe for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their bellies ſake, they aſſaulted true doctrine by theyr impure barking. It is as much as if he ſhould ſay, they were vncleane and prophane. Neither doo I agrée vnto them, who thinke they were ſo called, becauſe they did enuy others, or did bite them. Secondly, he calleth them <hi>Euill laborers,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that vnder the colour of edifying the Church, they did nothing but ouerthrowe and deſtroy all. For many labour much, whome it were better to be idle, as that common crier being aſked of <hi>Gracchus</hi> ieſtingly, becauſe he ſate idle, what he did, had his aunſwere in a readineſſe, yea what doeſt thou? for he was captaine of a pernicious tumult. <hi>Paule</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would haue a difference among laborers, that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full might beware of thoſe that are euill. In the third name there is an elegant <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. They did boaſt that they were circumciſion, he derideth this boaſting by calling it conciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe they did rent aſunder the vnitie of the Church, wherein we haue an example, that the holy Ghoſt in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments did not alwaies ſhun pleaſantneſſe and ieſting, from whom notwithſtanding ſcoffing muſt be far off, which beſéemeth not his maieſtie. There are infinite examples in the Prophetes, and eſpecially in <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſo that there is no prophane Author who aboundeth more with pleaſant allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of words and with figures. But we muſt more marke the vehemencie whereby <hi>Paule</hi> inueigheth agaynſte the falſe Apoſtles, whiche truely wyll burſt foorth, whereſoeuer there is the heate of a godly zeale. But wée muſt take héede that no intemperance or immoderate bitterneſſe procéede vnder the colour of zeale. Further, where he ſayth, that it is not troubleſome to him to write the ſame things vnto them, he ſeemeth to inferre that he hath otherwiſe written vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Philippians,</hi> but it ſhall not be abſurd ſo to take it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:7789:33"/> they are now admoniſhed of the ſame things by writing, which they had oft times heard when he was preſent. And it is no doubt but oft times he diſputed by wordes, how muche ſuch plagues were to be taken héede of, yet it gréeueth hym not to repeate the ſame thing, becauſe thorough ſilence there was daunger imminent vnto the <hi>Philippians.</hi> And truly it is the dutie of a good paſtor, not onely to miniſter foode vnto his flocke, and to gouerne them by his direction, but alſo to driue away the wolues that come néere the foldes, and that not once, but continually to ſtand vpon his watch, and neuer to be wearie, for ſéeing that théeues and robbers doo alwaies watch to the deſtruction of the Church, what excuſe ſhall it be for the paſtor, if after he hath ſometimes valiantly repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them, at the ninth or tenth aſſault he then fainteth? hée ſheweth that ſuch a repetition is profitable to the <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> leaſt (as ſometimes it commeth to paſſe) they ſhould be too proude, and contemne it as a thing ſuperfluous. For the moſt part of men are ſo wayward, that they can not abide the ſame thing to be twiſe ſpoken, neither in the meane while doo they thinke that, that which is daily beaten into them, doo ſcarſe at length after ten yeares ſticke in their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie. And if it were profitable for the <hi>Philippians</hi> to heare this exhortation of <hi>Paule,</hi> that they may diſcerne wolues, what meane the Papiſts, that they can abide no iudgement to be giuen of their doctrine? for whome I pray did <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeake vnto, when he ſaid <hi>Beware?</hi> did he not ſpeake vnto them, to whome they permit no right to diſcerne? and of them alſo Chriſt ſpeaketh in like manner: My ſhéepe heare my voice and follow me, a ſtraunger they flie from, and they doo not heare his voice. <hi>Iohn. 10.5.27. 3. <hi>For we are the Circumciſion.</hi>
                  </hi> That is, we are the true ſéede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and heires of the couenant, which was confirmed by the ſigne of circumciſion: for the true circumciſion is of the ſpirit, not of the letter, placed within in the head, not viſible concerning the fleſh. <hi>Rom. 2, 29.</hi> By ſpirituall worſhip he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that worſhip which is commended vnto vs in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7789:33"/> and conſiſteth of faith and calling vpon God, of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying of our ſelues, and of a pure conſcience. We muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand an antitheſis or contrarietie, becauſe by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarie he toucheth the worſhip preſcribed in the lawe, whiche the falſe Apoſtles only vrged, as if he ſhould ſay: they teach that God is worſhipped by outward obſeruations, and becauſe they obſerue the ceremonies of the lawe, they falſely boaſt that they are the people of God. We are truly circumciſed who worſhip God in ſpirit and truth. But héere ſome man will aſke whether the truth excludeth Sacraments, for the ſame thing may be ſaid of Baptiſme and of the Lord hys ſupper. I aunſwere, that that principle is alwaies to bée marked, that figures are abrogated by the comming of Chriſt, and circumciſion is changed into Baptiſme. From this principle it followeth, that pure and lawfull worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God is now frée from the ceremonies of the lawe, and true circumciſion vnto the faithfull conſiſt without a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. <hi>And we reioyce in Chriſt.</hi> The antitheſis muſt be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: we cleaue to the matter it ſelfe, whileſt they ſticke in ſignes: we abide in the bodie, whileſt they haue reſpect vnto ſhadowes. Neither doo the contrarie member of the ſentence which he ſet oppoſite agrée ill with this: we haue no truſt in the fleſh, for vnder the name of fleſh he comprehendeth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is outward in a man from whence glory is ſought, as it ſhall appeare out of the text, or that I may ſpeake more briefely, he calleth fleſhe whatſoeuer is without Chriſt, wherein he doth not lightly gaule theſe peruerſe followers of the lawe, becauſe not contented with Chriſt, they flie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorie of others. He put, <hi>To reioyce,</hi> and to haue truſt for the ſame, for thorough confidence he exalteth a man that he may alſo haue boldneſſe to reioyce, therefore they are things ioyned together. <hi>4 <hi>Although I alſo.</hi>
                  </hi> He ſpeaketh not of the affection, but he ſheweth that he alſo hath occaſion to reioice, if that he woulde imitate the fooliſhneſſe of others. The ſenſe therfore is thus: my glory is placed in Chriſt: but if I muſt néedes reioyce in the fleſhe, I want not matter
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7789:34"/> whereof to reioyce. And héereof we learne how their arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie is to be refuted, that are proude without Chriſt. If we alſo haue the ſame things, wherein they exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, let vs not ſuffer them by their fooliſh boaſting to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult vpon Chriſt, but let vs refuſe our owne glory, that they may vnderſtand, that it is not for enuie that we doo not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme, yea rather, that we willingly caſt away thoſe things which they make moſt accompt of. Let this notwithſtanding be alwaies a clauſe, that all truſt of the fleſhe is vaine and ridiculous. <hi>If any man hath whereof to truſt in the fleſhe, more I.</hi> Not contented to make himſelfe equall with any of them, he doth preferre himſelfe before them, wherefore he can not be ſuſpected in this cauſe as if he enuied their excellencie: and that he extolleth Chriſt to humble that which was wanting in himſelfe. He ſaith therefore, if it ſhould come into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, that he ſhall be more excellent than the others: for they had nothing (as we ſhall ſée by and by) which he had not in like manner common with them, and in ſome things he did farre ſurpaſſe them. He ſaid improperly that he had truſt, who without truſt was indued with carnall glorie, wherewith others were puffed vp. <hi>5 <hi>Circumciſed the eight day:</hi>
                  </hi> word for word, it is the circumciſion of the eight day, but touching the ſenſe, there is no difference, for it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that according to the lawfull cuſtome, and according to the preſcript of the lawe, that hée was circumciſed. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that ordinarie circumciſion, it was had in great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and beſide, it was a token of their kindred, whereof he addeth afterward. For in ſtrangers there was not the like reaſon, for after they were become Proſelites, they were circumciſed being yong men, or men growne to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and ſometimes alſo being old men. He ſaith there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that by kindred he is an Iſraelite. He ſheweth the tribe, not (in my iudgement) that the tribe of <hi>Beniamin</hi> had more excellencie than the reſt, but to confirme the credite of hys kindred. Hether alſo appertaine that whyche hée addeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne that hée is <hi>An Hebrewe of the Hebrewes:</hi> for this was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7789:34"/> an old name wherewith <hi>Abraham</hi> is adorned by <hi>Moyſes</hi> in <hi>Geneſis. 14, 13.</hi> The ſumme therfore is, that <hi>Paule</hi> from hys verie originall was borne of the ſéede of <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſo that from thence he might reckon hys graundfathers and great graundfathers. <hi>According to the lawe a Phariſee.</hi> After that hée had diſputed of the nobilitie of hys ſtocke, hée deſcendeth now vnto peculiar giftes of hys perſon (as they call them.) Commonly it is ſufficiently knowne, that the ſect of the Phariſes in opinion of holines and doctrine, was famous aboue the reſt, of that ſect he ſheweth that hée was. It is a common opinion that they were called Phariſes of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: but I rather allowe that which I heard ſometyme of <hi>Capito,</hi> a man of holie memorie, that they had their name from hence, becauſe they boaſted that they excelled in the gifte of interpreting the Scripture, for <hi>Phares</hi> among the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> is Interpretation. When others profeſſed themſelues to be learned, theſe men had rather be called Phariſes, who were ſkilfull in the interpretation of olde writers. And truly it is manifeſt, that vnder the colour of antiquitie, they corrupted the whole Scripture by their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet becauſe they kept ſtill certayne interpretations deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by the hands of their fathers, the greateſt honor was gyuen vnto them. But what meane thys clauſe, <hi>According to the lawe:</hi> for truely, there is nothyng more contrarie to the lawe of God, than ſectes, for there one truth of God is delyuered, whyche is the bonde of vnitie. Moreouer, that all ſectes ſproong vp when <hi>Ionathas</hi> was high Prieſt, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> witneſſeth in hys firſt booke of Antiquities, and <hi>13.</hi> Chapter. <hi>Paule</hi> vſeth improperlie the name of the lawe, for the doctrine of religion, becauſe it was verie corrupt at that time, as at thys daye is the Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in the Papacie. But becauſe there were manie of the order of the Doctors leſſe ſkilfull and exerciſed, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mention of hys owne zeale. This was an haynous offence in <hi>Paule</hi> to perſecute the Churche: but becauſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7789:35"/> he had to doo with varlets, who by mingling Chriſt with <hi>Moyſes,</hi> did pretend the zeale of the lawe. He ſheweth of the contrary ſide, that he was ſo earneſtly zealous for the lawe, that for this cauſe he was a perſecutor of the Church. <hi>Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the righteouſnes which is in the lawe.</hi> It is no doubt but héere he vnderſtandeth the whole righteouſnes of the lawe, for it is too barren to take it for the ceremonies only. The ſenſe therefore is more generall, that he embraced integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of life, ſo much as could be required of a profeſſor of the lawe. Againe it is obiected, that the righteouſnes of the law is perfect before God: for the ſumme is, that men altogether ſhould cleaue vnto God, and what can be more deſired vnto perfection? I aunſwere, that <hi>Paule</hi> héere ſpeaketh of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, whiche mighte ſatiſfie the common eſtimation of men, for he ſeparateth the lawe from Chriſt, and what is the lawe without Chriſt, but a dead letter? that the matter may appeare more playnely, I ſay there is a double righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of the lawe, one is ſpirituall, namely, the perfect loue of God and of our neighbours, that is contained in doctrine, and was neuer in the life of any man, the other is liberall, whiche appeareth in the ſight of men, when in the meane time hypocriſie reigneth in the heart, and there is nothing before God but iniquitie. So the lawe hath two reſpects, the one of God, and the other of men, <hi>Paule</hi> therefore was holy in the iudgement of men, and frée from all reprehenſion: a rare praiſe truly, and almoſt ſingular, yet let vs conſider how much he eſtéemed it.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </bibl> But the things that were aduantage vnto me, the ſame I counted loſſe for Chriſt his ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8</hi>
                     </bibl> Yea, I thinke all things but loſſe, for the excellencie of the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus my Lorde, for whome I haue made loſſe of all things, and I thinke them to be dong that I might winne Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>9</hi>
                     </bibl> And might find in him, not hauing mine owne righteouſnes, which is of the lawe, but that which is thorough faith of Chriſt, which I ſay is the righteouſnes in faith.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:7789:35"/>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>10</hi>
                     </bibl> That I may know him, and the power of his reſurrection, &amp; the fellowſhip of his afflictions, while I am made conformable vnto his death.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>11</hi>
                     </bibl> If by any meanes I might attaine to the reſurrection of the dead.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 <hi>The things that were aduantage vnto me:</hi>
                  </hi> he ſaith they were aduantage vnto him before he knewe Chriſt: for the only ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt doth cauſe that we are puffed vp with a vain confidence of our ſelues. Therefore whereſoeuer we ſée in any a falſe opinion of their owne vertue, wherſoeuer we ſée arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie, whereſoeuer we ſée pride, let vs knowe that Chryſte is not there known. Contrariwiſe, ſo ſoone as Chriſt ſhineth vnto vs, in a moment thoſe thinges vaniſhe or waxe vile, whatſoeuer did afore dazle our eyes with a falſe brightnes. Therefore thoſe things that were aduantage vnto <hi>Paule</hi> yet being blind, or rather thoſe things that had deceiued him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of aduantage, he acknowledgeth being illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, that they were loſſe vnto him: why did he thinke them loſſes? becauſe they were hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces vnto him, that he could not come vnto Chriſt: And what is more hurtfull than that which driueth vs from acceſſe vnto Chriſt? But he ſpeaketh eſpecially of his owne righteouſnes: for we are not admitted vnto Chriſt, except we be empty and voide of our owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vertue: Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> did acknowledge that there was nothing more hurtful vnto him than his owne righteouſnes, as whereby he was excluded from Chriſt. <hi>8. <hi>Yea I thinke all things but loſſe.</hi>
                  </hi> This doth ſignifie that he did abide ſtedfaſt in his opinion, becauſe oftentimes it come to paſſe, that béeyng carried away with a delight of nouelties, we forget all other things, and afterwarde it repenteth vs. Wherefore <hi>Paule</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſaide that he had renounced all impediments, that he might poſſeſſe Chriſt: he now addeth that he is ſtill of that minde. <hi>For the excellencie of the knowledge.</hi> Be extolleth the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell againſte all perſuaſions which doe deceiue vs: for many things ſéeme to be excellent, but the knowledge of Chriſt ſo farre excéedeth all things in excellency, that in reſpect of that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7789:36"/> only there is nothing but contemptible: hereof therefore let vs learne, how much the knowledge of Chriſt only is to bée eſtéemed. Whereas he calleth him his Lord, he doth that to expreſſe the vehemencie of his affection <hi>For whom I haue made loſſe of all things.</hi> He ſaith more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before, at leaſt he ſpeaketh more ſignificantly: the ſimilitude is taken from ſailers, who when they are in danger of ſhipwrack, caſt forth al thinges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the ſhip is vnladen, they may come ſafe into the hauen. Therfore <hi>Paule</hi> had rather be ſpoiled of all things whiche he had, than to be depriued of Chriſt only. But a queſtion may he aſked: whither it be neceſſary that we renounce riches, &amp; honors, &amp; nobility of kinred, &amp; alſo our outward righteouſnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may be made partakers of Chriſt, for all thoſe are gifts of god of themſelues not to be deſpiſed. I anſwere that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle doth not here ſpeake ſo much of the things themſelues, as of the quality of them. Indéed it is true that the kingdome of heauen is like to a pretious pearle, for the obtaining wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no man ſhould doubt to ſel all that he hath: but in things the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is one, &amp; the quality another. It was not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for <hi>Paule</hi> to renounce his tribe and the ſtocke of <hi>Abraham</hi> and to be of another nation, that he might become a chriſtian: but to caſt away the confidence of his kinred. He ſhoulde not of a chaſt man become vnſhamefaſt, of a ſober man intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, of a graue and honeſt man become diſſolute: but to put off the falſe perſwaſion of his owne righteouſnes, and to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr it. We alſo do not diſpute againſt the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of works when we handle the righteouſnes of faith: but againſte that quality which the Sophiſters giue them, becauſe they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that by them men are iuſtified. <hi>Paule</hi> therfore ſpoiled himſelfe, not of his works, but of the peruerſe confidence in his works, wherwith he was puffed. Concerning riches and honors, when we haue laide away the affection of them, we ſhall alſo be ready to caſt away the things themſelues, as oft as god ſhall require it, and it ſo behoueth vs. It is not ſimply neceſſary, that thou ſhouldeſt be poore, that thou myghteſt be a Chriſtian: but if it ſhall ſo pleaſe the Lorde, it is méete
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7789:36"/> that thou ſhouldeſt be ready to abide pouerty. To conclude it is not lawful for chriſtians to haue any thing without Chriſt That I ſay is without Chriſt whatſoeuer hinder vs that we glory not in Chriſt only, &amp; that he rule not altogither in vs. <hi>And I thinke them to be dongue.</hi> Here not only in words, but in matter alſo he much amplifieth that which before he ſaide: for they that caſt away their wares and other things into the ſea, that they may eſcape ſafely, they doe not therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne riches: but becauſe they had rather liue in miſery and pouerty, than to be drowned with their owne ſubſtance: yet they loſe them very hardly and with groning, and when they haue eſcaped, they bewaile the loſſe of them. <hi>Paule</hi> contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affirmeth that he had not only forſaken whatſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he accounted pretious: but that they did ſmell vnto hym like dongue, or become vile like thoſe things whiche are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteouſly caſt forth. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> interpreteth it chaffe: but the grammarians thynke that it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that which is caſt vnto dogges: and truly whatſoeuer thing is ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge from Chriſt, it ſhould ſtinke vnto vs, becauſe it is abomination before god, and it ought alſo to be vile vnto vs, becauſe it is nothing but a falſe imagination. <hi>That I might gaine Chriſt.</hi> By this word he noteth that Chriſt cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be gained, except we loſe al things that are our own: for he wil haue vs to be rich by his grace only: he alone will bée our happines. What maner of loſing he here ſpeak of, it was ſaid before: namely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothing ſhould withdrawe vs from the truſt in Chriſt only. And if <hi>Paule</hi> in that innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; integrity of life, doubted not to account his righteouſnes for loſſe and dongue, what meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phariſes of theſe dayes, who being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raied with all kinde of wickednes are not yet aſhamed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll their owne merits againſt Chriſt. <hi>And might find in him.</hi> It is a verbe paſſiue, which he here vſeth: &amp; therefore al other haue tranſlated it <hi>And I might be found:</hi> but they paſſe ouer the text very coldly, as though there were no emphaſis in it. If you reade it paſſiuely, a contrariety muſt be vnderſtoode: that <hi>Paule</hi> was loſte afore he was found in Chriſt: as a riche merchant is like vnto one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is loſt, ſo long as he hath his ſhip
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7789:37"/> laden with wealth, and after all is caſt away he is founde: for here that ſaying is of value. <hi>I had periſhed if I had not peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> But becauſe the verb <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the paſſiue termination hath an actiue ſignification, &amp; then it ſignifie to recouer that which thou haſt willingly parted from (as <hi>Budeus</hi> ſheweth by many examples) I haue not doubted to alter from the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of others: for by this meanes the ſenſe ſhal be more ful, and the doctrine more plentiful: namely, that <hi>Paule</hi> renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced all things whiche he had, that he might recouer them in Chriſt: and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> anſwereth better to the word gaine, becauſe it ſignifie, that it is no ſmal or common gaine, ſeing that Chriſt containeth all things in him ſelfe. And truly we loſe nothing when we come vnto Chriſt naked and empty, becauſe we the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> begin to obtaine thoſe things, which before we falſly thought that we had. Therefore he declareth better how greate the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſte are, becauſe in him we obtaine and finde all things. <hi>Not hauing mine owne righteouſnes.</hi> A notable place if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſire to haue a certaine definition of the righteouſnes of faith, and to holde the true nature therof: for <hi>Paule</hi> here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth two righteouſneſſes togither: The one he ſaith is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vnto man, the which he calleth the righteouſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law: the other he teacheth to be from GOD, and to be obtained through faith, and to be repoſed in the faith of Chriſt, theſe he maketh ſo contrary betwéene them ſelues, that they can not ſtande togither. Two things therefore are here to be noted, that thou muſt giue ouer, and reſigne the righteouſnes of the lawe, that thou maieſt be righteous by faith: then that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes of faith procéede from God, and is not proper vnto man. Touching both of theſe, there is great contentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this day betwixt vs and the Papiſts: for neyther doe they grant that the righteouſnes of faith is altogither from GOD: but they attribute part vnto man: and they mingle them togither as though the one did not take away the other. Therfore we muſt diligently weigh all the wordes of <hi>Paule,</hi> becauſe there is none of them wherein there is not great moment: he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the faithfull haue any righteouſnes of their own: but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7789:37"/> it can not be denied, but if there were anye righteouſnes of workes, it might worthily be called ours: therfore he leaueth no place at al for the righteouſnes of works. Why he calleth it the righteouſnes of the lawe he ſheweth. <hi>Rom. 10.5.</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe this is the edict of the law: he that doth theſe things ſhall liue in them, therefore the lawe doth pronounce a man to be iuſt by his workes, neyther can the papiſts cauil that al this muſt be reſtrained vnto ceremonies: for firſt it is a friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous triflyng that <hi>Paule</hi> was only righteous by ceremonies: then by this reaſon he oppoſeth theſe two righteouſneſſes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one is proper vnto man, the other is from God: therefore the one doth ſignifie the rewarde of works: the other the frée gift of God. So generally he oppoſeth the merit of man vnto the grace of Chriſt: for when the lawe bringeth workes, faith of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth a naked man vnto God, that he may be clothed with the righteouſnes of Chriſt. Whereas therefore he affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the righteouſnes of faith is from God, it is not only becauſe faith is the gift of God, but becauſe God of his goodnes doo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vs, or elſe becauſe by faith we receiue the righteouſnes whiche he hathe giuen vs. <hi>10. <hi>That I may knowe him.</hi>
                  </hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the force &amp; nature of faith, namely that it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt, and that not naked or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed: but whileſt the vertue of his reſurrection is perceiued, he put reſurrection for the accompliſhment of redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo that it containeth death vnder it: but becauſe it is little to know Chriſt crucified, and raiſed from the deade, except thou doeſt apprehende the fruite thereof, he ſpeaketh namely of the efficacie. Then therefore Chriſt is knowne aryght, when we féele what his death and reſurrection doe preuaile in vs, and how effectuall he is in vs: for there all thyngs are ſet out vnto vs: the taking awaye of ſin, deliuerie from guiltines, ſatiſfaction, the victory of death, the obtaining of righteouſnes, and the hope of bleſſed immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie. <hi>And the fellowſhip of his paſſions.</hi> After he had ſpoken of frée righteouſnes, which being gotten by the reſurrection of Chriſt, we obtaine through faith: he ioyneth the exerciſes of the godly, &amp; that leaſt it ſhould ſéeme that he bring in an idle
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7789:38"/> faith which bringeth forth no effectes in their life, &amp; he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that theſe are the ſtudies wherein the Lord woulde haue his children exerciſed: though the falſe Apoſtles thruſt vpon them the bare elements of ceremonies. He therefore that by faith is made partaker of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods of Chriſt, let him know that this condition is propounded vnto him, that all his lyfe muſt be made conformable to his death. But there is a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fellowſhip and communicating of the death of Chriſt, the one is within, which the ſcripture is wont to call the morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the fleſh, or the crucifiyng of the old man: wherof <hi>Paule</hi> entreateth <hi>Rom. 6.</hi> The other is without which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the mortifiyng of the outward man, that is the bearing of the croſſe, whereof he entreateth in the <hi>8.</hi> chapter of the ſame epiſtle, and here alſo, except I be deceiued: for after we haue comprehended the vertue of his reſurrection, Chriſte is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto vs crucified, that by tribulations and ſorrows we ſhoulde follow him, and therefore the reſurrection of the dead is fitly expreſſed, that we may knowe that we muſt dye before we liue. This is the continual meditation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſo long as they are ſtrangers in the earth: but this is an excellent conſolation, that in all our miſeries we are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the croſſe of Chriſt, if we be his members, that by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions the way is made open for vs vnto eternall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as it is ſaide. <hi>2. Tim. 2.11.</hi> If we dy with him we ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo liue with him, if we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo raygne with him. It is méete therefore that we al ſhould be brought vnto this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our whole life ſhould repreſent vnto vs nothiyng but an image of death, vntill it bring forth death it ſelfe. As the life of Chriſt was nothing elſe but a forerunner of death: but in the meane while we haue this comfort, that the end is euerlaſting bleſſednes: for the death of Chriſt is ioyned with his reſurrection. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, that he is made con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable vnto his death, that he may come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of hys reſurrection. This part <hi>If by any meanes</hi> procéede not of doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but it noteth the hardnes of it to ſtir vp our deſire: for it is not a lyght combate, when we ſtriue with ſo many and ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7789:38"/> great hinderances.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>12</hi>
                     </bibl> Not as though I had already obtained it, or were alreadye perfect, but I follow that I alſo may comprehende, euen as I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>13</hi>
                     </bibl> Brethren, I thinke that I haue not yet comprehended it, but one thing I doe, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauoring my ſelfe vnto thoſe things which are before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>14.</hi>
                     </bibl> I follow toward the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>15</hi>
                     </bibl> Let vs therfore as many as be perfect be thus minded: and if ye be otherwiſe minded, God ſhall reueale euen this thyng vnto you</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>16</hi>
                     </bibl> Neuertheleſſe whither we are come, that we may minde one thing: let vs proceede by the ſame rule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </bibl> And togither brethren be followers of me, and conſider the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which walke ſo, euen as ye haue vs for an example.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 <hi>Not as though I had already obtained it.</hi> Paule</hi> laboreth in this that he might perſwade the philippians, that he think on nothing but Chriſt, that he is wiſe in no other thing, that he deſire no other thing, that he is occupied in no other medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: herevnto it auaileth much which he now addeth, that he which had renounced al hindrances, had not yet attaind to the marke: &amp; therfore he did laboure and endeauour to come further: how much more ſhould the Philippians ſtriue, who as yet were far from him? But a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be aſked what it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paule</hi> ſaithe, he haue not yet obtained: for truly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are engraffed by faith into the body of Chriſte we are alreadye entered into the kingdome of God, and as it is ſaide <hi>Eph. 2.6.</hi> we ſit already by hope in heauenly places. I anſwere that our ſaluation is in the meane tyme placed in hope, that our inheritance may be certaine, notwithſtanding as yet we doe not enioy the poſſeſſion of it. Althoughe <hi>Paule</hi> here reſpecteth the encreaſe of fayth, and mortification, whereof he ſpake afore. He ſaide that he did ſtriue and labor vnto the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the dead, by the fellowſhip of the croſſe of Chriſte: he addeth that as yet he hath not attayned to this: to what? namely that he might certainely communicate
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7789:39"/> with the paſſions of Chriſt, that he might haue a perfect taſte of the power of his reſurrection, that he might knowe hym plainely. Therefore by his owne example, he admoniſheth them that they muſt goe forward, and that the knowledge of Chriſt is a thing of ſuch hardenes, that they which laboure in that only, are notwithſtanding neuer perfect ſo long as they liue. Moreouer this doth nothing derogate from the doctrine of <hi>Paule,</hi> becauſe he had comprehended ſo much as was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to execute the charge committed vnto him. In the mean time it behoued him to go forward that the diuine teacher of all men might be inſtructed vnto humilitie. <hi>Euen as he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended.</hi> He put in this clauſe by the way of correction, that he might attribute all his endeauour vnto the grace of God. It ſkilleth not muche whither you reade it <hi>Euen as,</hi> or <hi>So farre as:</hi> for the ſenſe remaineth all on, that <hi>Paule</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of Chriſte, that he might comprehende Chriſte, that is, that he did nothing, but by the motion and the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt:: yet I haue choſen that which was more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, ſince that his wiſh ſéemed to be frée. <hi>I thinke that I haue not yet comprehended it.</hi> He doth not here cal the faith of his ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into doubt, as though he were yet in ſuſpence, but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peateth that which he had ſaide, that he did yet ſtriue to goe forwarde, becauſe he had not yet come to the ende of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. And that he declareth continually, ſaying, that he was only buſied in that, leauing all other thinges. He compareth our life vnto a race, the ſpace wherof that we haue to runne, God haue limited vnto vs: for as it nothing profiteth a run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner if he ſet forth, except he come to the ende of the race: ſo we alſo muſt finiſh the courſe of our vocation euen vnto deathe, neither muſte we ceaſe before we haue obtained that whyche we deſire. Beſides, as the way is limited for the runner, leaſt by ſtraying hither and thither, he ſhoulde weary him ſelfe in vaine, in comming nothing at all forwarde vnto the goale: ſo there is alſo a marke propounded vnto vs, whither we muſt rightly direct our courſe: neither doth God ſuffer vs raſhly to ſtraie abroade. Thirdly, as a runner muſt be ſwift, &amp; to ſtaye
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7789:39"/> his pace at no delaies, but neglecting all, to continue on hys courſe: ſo we muſt beware that we yéeld not our mind vnto any thing that might call vs away, but we muſt rather en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour, that being frée from all hinderances, we may apply our whole ſtudie only vnto the calling of God. Theſe thrée things <hi>Paule</hi> comprehendeth in one ſimilitude, where hée ſaith, that he doth this one thing, and that he forget all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer things, he expreſſeth his courage, and excludeth all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments. When he ſaith that he follow hard towarde the marke, it ſignifieth that he doth not wander out of the way. <hi>Forgetting the things that are behinde.</hi> He alludeth vnto run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, who neuer turne backe their eies, leaſt they ſhoulde ſlacken the ſwiftneſſe of their courſe, eſpecially they looke not backward, how much ground they haue gone, but they haſte right on vnto the goale. So <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth, that he doth not conſider who he is, nor what he hath done, but only that hée endeuour vnto the appointed marke, and that with ſuch ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, as if with ſtretched armes he were carried thether, for there is ſuche a metaphore in the participle which he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. If any woulde obiect that the remembrance of our life paſt, is auaileable to ſtirre vs vp, as well becauſe the graces alreadie beſtowed vpon vs doo encourage vs to hope well, as alſo becauſe we are admoniſhed by our ſinnes, that our life is to be amended for better: I anſwere, that ſuch cogitations do not turne our eies backward, but rather helpe the ſharpenes of our ſight, that more cléerely we may behold the marke. But <hi>Paule</hi> héere condemneth thoſe reſpects, which doo either breake off, or diminiſh our chéerefulnes, euen as if any man, being perſuaded that he hath gone forward inough, becauſe he ſéemeth to himſelfe to haue done his dutie, will wax ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and will deliuer his lampe vnto others: or if any man be moued with the deſire of the condition which he haue left, he can not apply his whole ſtudie vnto that which he doth. Such were the cogitations from the which it was neceſſarie that <hi>Paule</hi> his mind ſhould be withdrawne, if he would ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly follow the vocation of Chriſt. But becauſe mention
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7789:40"/> was héere made of endeuour, of ſtudie, of running, and of perſeuerance, leaſt any ſhould thinke that ſaluation is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in them, or ſhould aſcribe vnto the diligence of men that which procéedeth from another. Willing to note out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of all, he added in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>15. <hi>Let vs therefore as manie as be perfect.</hi>
                  </hi> Leaſt any ſhould take this to be ſpoken of the common ſort of men, as though he preſcribed rudiments vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are children in Chriſt: he teſtifieth, that it is a rule which all they that are perfect ſhould obſerue. And this rule is, that we muſt renounce confidence in all things, that we may reioyce in the onely righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and neglecting all things, may attaine vnto the fellowſhip of his paſſions, which may leade vs vnto a bleſſed reſurrection. Where now ſhall be the ſtate of perfection which the Monks feigne? where ſhall be their confuſed fardell of ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions? to conclude, where ſhall all Papiſtrie become, which is nothing elſe but an imagined perfection, and which agréeth not with this rule of <hi>Paule?</hi> truely, whoſoeuer ſhall vnderſtand this one word, ſhall cléerely perceiue that thoſe things are filthie dong whatſoeuer the Papiſtes teache tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching righteouſneſſe and obteining of ſaluation. <hi>If yee bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded.</hi> He humbleth their works and them, and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them vp vnto a good hope. For he admoniſheth them, that they ſhould not be proude in their ignorance, and yet he biddeth them bée of good chéere, when he ſayth, that they muſt looke for the reuelation of God, for we knowe how great an hinderance of the truth obſtinacie is. This therefore is an excellent preparation vnto teaching, if we doo not pleaſe our ſelues in our error. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> couertly doth ſhewe, that we muſt giue place vnto the reuelation of God, if as yet we haue not obteined that whiche wée ſéeke. And when he teacheth that we muſt procéede by degrées, he encourageth them, that they ſhould not faint in the middle of their courſe, although he alſo affirmeth that it is without controuerſie which he had taught, ſaying, that vnto them which diſagrée from him, that ſhall be reuealed which as yet they knowe
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7789:40"/> not: for it is as much as if he had ſayde, the Lorde will at ſometime ſhewe vnto you the ſame thing which I haue ſayd is the perfect rule to be rightly wiſe, and to liue well. No man coulde lawfully ſpeake ſo, but hée that were certayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie perſuaded of the reaſon and truth of his doctrine. In the meane time alſo let vs learne out of this place, that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for a time in our weake bréethren muſt bée ſuffered, and wée muſt pardon them if it bée not foorthwith graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them altogether to ſubſcribe vnto vs. <hi>Paule</hi> was certayne of hys doctrine, notwithſtanding he giueth vnto them a ſpace to profite, that as yet could not receiue it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he therefore ceaſe to accompt them as bréethren, only he taketh héede that they ſhould not flatter themſelues in their error. Whereas the Latine bookes haue, <hi>He hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed</hi> in the Pretertenſe, I eaſily reiect it, as being vnſit, and not agréeing with the matter. <hi>16 <hi>Neuertheleſſe whether we are come.</hi>
                  </hi> In the diſtinction the Gréeke examples alſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, for in ſome there are two whole ſentences, if the diuiſion rather pleaſe you, the ſenſe ſhall be that which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> hath giuen, but I rather embrace a diuerſe reading, that <hi>Paule</hi> exhorteth them to the imitation of himſelfe, that at length they may come to the ſame marke, namely, that they may thinke one thing, and may procéede by the ſame rule: for where ſincere affection flouriſheth, ſuch as ruled in <hi>Paule,</hi> there is an eaſie way vnto holy and godly concord. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe as yet they had not perceyued what true perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was, that they might come thether, hée woulde haue them followers of himſelfe, that is, with a pure conſcience to ſéeke God, to arrogate nothing to themſelues, quietly to ſubmit theyr ſenſes vnto Chriſt. For in the imitation of <hi>Paule</hi> all theſe vertues are contained, a right zeale, the feare of the Lord, modeſtie, denying of himſelfe, readineſſe to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, loue, and a deſire of concord. He biddeth them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether bée followers of him, that is, all with one conſent and with one minde. Note, that the marke of perfection, vnto the which he inuiteth the <hi>Philippians</hi> by his owne example, is,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7789:41"/> that they ſhould thinke the ſame thing, and procéede by the ſame rule, but before he put the doctrine, wherin they ſhould agrée, and the rule whervnto they ſhould frame themſelues. <hi>17 <hi>Conſider them.</hi>
                  </hi> By this word he ſignifieth, that they had others as well whome they might chooſe to imitate, ſo that they framed themſelues vnto that puritie whereof he was an example, whereby all ſuſpition of ambition is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waie: for whoſoeuer is addicted to hymſelfe, refuſeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions. And hée alſo admoniſheth them, that all indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentlie are not to bée followed, as hée addeth more playne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </bibl> For many walke, of whome I haue tolde you often, and nowe tell you weeping: that they are the enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </bibl> Whoſe end is destruction, whoſe God is their bellie, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to their ſhame, minding earthly things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </bibl> But our conuerſation is in heauen, from whence we looke for the ſauiour, euen the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </bibl> Who ſhall transforme our humble bodie, that it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to his glorious bodie, according to the working whereby he is able to ſubdue all things vnto himſelfe.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18 <hi>For many.</hi>
                  </hi> This in my iudgement is a ſimple propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: many walke minding earthly things: wherby he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that there are many which créepe vpon the ground, not féeling the power of the kingdome of God. He hath inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted marks, whereby ſuch may be knowne, which we will examine in their place. Some by earthly things vnderſtand ceremonies, and the outward elements of the world whiche bring in the forgetfulneſſe of true godlineſſe, but I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refer it vnto the carnall affection, namely, becauſe they not being regenerate by the ſpirit of God, doo ſauour in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the world, which ſhall appeare more plainely out of that which followeth. For héereby he bringeth them into enuie, becauſe they being only deſirous of their owne honor, eaſe, and gaine, did neglect the edifying of the Church. <hi>Of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7789:41"/> whome I haue told you often.</hi> He ſheweth how, that touching this matter he hath oft admoniſhed the <hi>Philippians,</hi> becauſe he now goeth about by his letters to reduce the ſame things into their memories, which he had before told them being preſent. And his teares are an argument that he was not moued with emulation, or hatred of the men, nor with a deſire of railing, or with the ſharpeneſſe of his wit, but with a godlie zeale, becauſe he ſawe that the Churche was miſerablie deſtroyed by ſuch plagues. So in lyke manner it behoueth vs to be affected, that when we ſée the paſtors place occupyed by wicked men, and men of no accompt, we ſhould grone, and at leaſt by teares teſtifie, that we are grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the calamitie of the Churche. It is alſo worth the noting, to conſider of whome <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh, not of open enemies, who by profeſſion deſired the deſtruction of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but of drones and varlets, who for ambition, or for their bellies ſake, did deſtroie the vertue of the Goſpell. Truely ſometime they ſhall knowe ſuche, who by ſéeking themſelues, doo more weaken the ſtrength of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, than if they did openlie reſiſt Chriſt: therefore we muſt not ſpare them, but poynt them out with our finger ſo oft as it is expedient, let them complaine afterward as they liſt of our ſeueritie, ſo that they obiect nothing agaynſt vs, which wée may not defend by the example of <hi>Paule. <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the croſſe.</hi>
                  </hi> Some expounde the croſſe for the whole my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of our redemption, and this they interprete to be ſaid, that by preaching the lawe, they did make the benefite of Chriſt his death to be of none effect. But others expounde it, that they fled from the croſſe, and woulde not put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in danger for Chriſt. I take it more generally, that faigning themſelues to be friends, they were the worſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Goſpell. Neither is it a rare thing with <hi>Paule,</hi> to ſet out the whole preaching of the Goſpell vnder the name of the croſſe: for as hée ſayeth in another place, if any bée in Chriſt, hée is a new creature. <hi>19 <hi>Whoſe ende is destru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </hi> Hée addeth this, that the <hi>Philippians</hi> béeing terrified
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7789:42"/> by the danger, might more diligentlie take héede, and not entangle themſelues in theyr deſtruction, and becauſe ſuch knaues by bragging and diuerſe artes doo oftentimes for a while blinde the eyes of the ſimple, that they are preferred euen before the good ſeruants of Chriſt: the Apoſtle with great boldnes pronounceth, that their glorie wherewith they are now puffed, ſhall bée turned into ſhame. <hi>Whoſe God is their bellie.</hi> Whereas they vrged Circumciſion and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, hée denieth that they doo it for a zeale of the lawe, but for the fauour of men, that they might liue quiet and without trouble, for they did ſée the Iewes to be maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fierce againſt <hi>Paule</hi> and ſuche like, neither could they preache Chriſt truely with any other condition, but they muſt ſtirre vp the ſame rage againſt themſelues, therefore prouiding for their eaſe and commoditie, they mingled thoſe corruptions which myghte extinguiſhe the heate of others. <hi>But our conuerſation is in heauen.</hi> This ſentence beateth downe all vayne pompes, wherewith the counterfaite mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell were wont to boaſt themſelues: and hatefully he inueigheth againſt all their attempts, becauſe that flying aboue the earth, they can not aſpire vnto heauen, for he teacheth that all things are nothing to be eſtéemed beſides the ſpirituall kingdome of God. Moreouer, that the faithfull muſt liue an heauenlie life in this worlde, as if hée ſhoulde ſay, they mind earthly things, therefore it is méete that wée ſhoulde bée eſtraunged from them, whoſe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is in heauen. We are héere mingled with infidels and hypocrites, yea, the chaffe appeare in the Lorde hys floore aboue the wheate. Beſides, we are ſubiect vnto the common miſeries of this earthlie life, we want meate and drinke, and other neceſſaries, notwithſtanding in minde and affection wée muſt bée conuerſant in heauen: for wée muſt paſſe ſwiftly thorough this lyfe, and we muſt be dead to the worlde, that Chriſt may liue in vs, and we in like manner liue vnto him. This place is a moſt plentifull foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of manie exhortations, which any man may eaſily
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7789:42"/> gather out. <hi>From whence alſo.</hi> By the coniunction that wée haue in Chriſt, he proueth that our gouernement is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For it is not méete that the members ſhould bée diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from their head, therefore ſéeing that Chriſt is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that wée may cleaue vnto hym, it is neceſſarie that in oure mindes wée dwell out of the worlde. Beſides, where our treaſure is, there our heart is alſo. Chriſt our bleſſedneſſe and glorie is in the heauens, therefore let our ſoules dwell alofte with hym, therefore by name hée cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth hym a Sauioure. From whence haue wée ſaluation? namely, Chriſt our Sauiour ſhall come vnto vs from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, therefore it is abſurd that wée ſhoulde bée buſied in the earth. Thys epithete of a Sauioure ſerueth the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of the place, for therefore wée are ſayde in oure myndes to bée in heauen, becauſe from thence onely the hope of ſaluation ſhineth vnto vs. The comming of Chriſte as it ſhall bée terrible vnto the vngodlie, ſo it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turneth away theyr myndes from heauen, than ſtirreth them vp thither. For they knowe that there ſhall come a Iudge for them, and as much as is in them, they flée from hym. Out of theſe wordes of <hi>Paule</hi> the godlie ſoules gather a ſwéete conſolation, when they heare that they muſt deſire the comming of Chriſt, becauſe it ſhall bée healthfull for them. Contrarywiſe, it is a certayne ſigne of incredulitie, at euerie mention thereof to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, looke the eyght Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> but whileſt others are carried about with vayne deſires, <hi>Paule</hi> wyll haue the faythfull contented with Chriſt onely. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, wée learne out of thys place, that wée muſt imagine no baſe or earthly thyng of Chriſt, becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs looke vp into heauen, that wée may ſéeke hym. But they that ſubtelly diſpute that Chriſt is not enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or thruſt into one corner of heauen, that thence they mighte prooue hys bodie to bée euerie where, and that hée filleth heauen and earth, they neyther ſaye anye
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7789:43"/> thing, nor all: for as it were raſh and fooliſh to aſcend be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the heauens, and in this or that countrey to aſſigne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt a ſtanding, ſitting, or walking: ſo in like manner, to drawe him out of heauen by any carnall cogitation that we might ſéeke him in earth, it is a fooliſh and pernicious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, therefore let our hearts be aloft, that they may be with the Lord. <hi>21 <hi>Who ſhall transforme.</hi>
                  </hi> By this argument he pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth yet more the <hi>Philippians</hi> forward, that their minds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lift vp into heauen, they may cleaue altogether vnto Chriſt. Becauſe this bodie which we beare about is no conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall dwelling, but a ruinous tabernacle, which ſhall ſoone be brought to nothing: beſides, it is ſubiect to ſo many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and ſo many ſhamefull infirmities, that it may rightly be called abiect and full of ſhame, but from whence muſt we hope for the reſtoring thereof? from heauen, at the comming of Chriſt, therefore there is no part of vs, which with our whole deſire ſhould not aſpire into heauen. We ſée the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent baſeneſſe of our bodies in life, but eſpecially in death. The glorie which they ſhall haue conformable to the bodie of Chriſt, is incomprehenſible: for if the diſciples could not abide the ſmall taſte he gaue them in the Tranſfiguration, which of vs can attaine vnto the fulneſſe thereof? let vs now be contente with the teſtimonie of our adoption, we ſhall knowe the riches of our inheritance, when we ſhall enioie them. <hi>According to the working.</hi> Becauſe there is nothing more incredible, nor more diſagréeing from the ſenſe of the fleſh, that the reſurrection, for this cauſe <hi>Paule</hi> ſetteth the infinite power of God before our eies, the which ſhoulde ſwallow vp all doubting: for thereof ariſeth diſtruſt, becauſe we meaſure the thing by the narrownes of our owne wit. Neither did he ſaie only <hi>Power,</hi> but <hi>Effectuall working,</hi> which is the effect, or ſuch a power that bringeth it ſelfe into acte (as I may ſo ſpeake) when it commeth into our minds that God, who hath created all things of nothing, can commaund the ſea and the land and the other elements, to reſtore that which hath béene put in them: foorthwith our mindes are
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7789:43"/> erected into a ſtrong hope, &amp; as it were into a ſpirituall ſight of the reſurrection. And it is not amiſſe alſo to mark, that the right &amp; power to raiſe the dead, yea to do all things according to his own wil is beſtowed on the perſon of Chriſt: by which praiſe, his diuine maieſty is excellently beautified. Moreouer hereof we gather y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the world was created by him: becauſe to ſubmit al things to himſelf, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth not but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creator.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chapter .4.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herfore my Brethren beloued &amp; longed for, my ioy, &amp; my crowne ſo ſtand in the Lord my beloued</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2</hi>
                        </bibl> I exhort Euodia, &amp; I exhort Syntiche, that they be of one accord in the Lord.</p>
                     <p>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>3</hi>
                        </bibl> Yea I beſeech thee alſo faithfull yokefellowe, helpe thoſe women which labored with me in the Goſpel, with Clement &amp; with my other helpers, whoſe names are in the booke of life.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Herfore Brethren.</hi> He ſhutteth vp his exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with more veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t words than he was accuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might the more déepely imprint it in mens minds. And he inſinuateth into their affections with ſwéete appellations, whyche notwithſtanding procéed not of flattery, but of a ſincere loue. He calleth them his ioy, and his crowne, becauſe he being glad that they gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his trauell did continue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for that triumph, whereof we ſpake, when the Lord ſhal crowne our déeds with his own happines. Where he biddeth them <hi>ſo ſtand in the Lord,</hi> he ſignifieth that he alloweth theyr eſtate, although this word <hi>So</hi> might be referred to the former doctrine: but that is more fit, that by praiſing their preſent ſtate, he might exhort them to perſeuerance: indéed they had already ſhewed ſome token of their conſtancie: yet <hi>Paule</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing priuie vnto mans weakenes, thinke that they haue néede to be confirmed for the time afterward <hi>2. <hi>I exhort</hi> Euodia <hi>&amp;</hi> Syntiche.</hi> It is a common opinion receiued for the moſt part, that <hi>Paule</hi> would quiet (I knowe not what grudge) betwéen theſe two women, touching which matter, although I would not contend: yet the coniecture in the words of <hi>Paule</hi> is ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7789:44"/> than that it can perſwade me that it was ſo: It appeareth by the teſtimony which he giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they were very wiſe women, for he attributeth ſo much vnto them, that he calleth them fellow laborers in the goſpel, therefore becauſe in their agrement there was much moment, &amp; in their diſcord greate danger, he encourageth them peculiarly vnto concorde. We muſt marke alſo, that ſo oft as he ſpeaketh of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent he addeth this band <hi>In the Lord.</hi> For without the Lord al agrement ſhal be accurſed, and there is nothing ſo diſſeuered, whiche muſte not in Chriſte againe be gathered togither. <hi>Yea and I beſeeche thee alſo faithfull yokefellow.</hi> I wil not diſpute of the ſexe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whither he ſpeaketh to a man or to a woman I leaue it indifferent, although the argument of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> be too weake, who gathereth therof that it was a woman, becauſe mention is here made of women, as though he doth not immediately adde the name of <hi>Clement</hi> in the ſame cauſe: but I ceaſe from that diſputation, only I déeme that the wife of <hi>Paule</hi> is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnder this name. They that affirme this, do cite <hi>Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> and <hi>Ignatius</hi> for the authors of it, if they did cite them truly, I woulde not diſpiſe ſuche men eſpecially. But ſéeing that counterfaite writings are brought forth by <hi>Euſebius:</hi> and added by the vnlearned munkes, they deſerue but little cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with readers of ſound iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therfore let vs enquire of the matter without the preiudice of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When <hi>Paule</hi> writ the firſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians, he reporteth that he then was vnmarried. <hi>1. Cor. 7.8.</hi> To them (he ſaith) that are vnmarried and to widowes I ſpeake: it is good if they conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue euen as I am. He wrote that epiſtle at <hi>Epheſus</hi> when he was ready to depart. Not long after he came to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> where he was caſt into priſon, and brought vnto <hi>Rome.</hi> How vnfit a tyme was thys to marrye a wyfe, whiche he ſpente partelye in hys iourney, and partelye in bondes, who ſeeth not? Adde herevnto that he was then readye to endure bondes &amp; perſecutions, as he witneſſeth in <hi>Luke, Act. 21.13.</hi> Neyther am I ignorant what is wonte to bée obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on the contrary parte: namely that <hi>Paule</hi> being marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7789:44"/> did abſtaine from the company of hys wife. But the wordes ſounde otherwyſe: for he wiſheth that they which are vnmarried, myght continue in his eſtate. And what is hys eſtate but the ſtate of ſinglenes? Whereas they bryng in that: Is it not lawfull for me to leade about a wife? <hi>1. Cor. 9.5.</hi> to proue that he had a wife, it is too friuolous, ſo that it néede no anſwere. But now that we may grante that <hi>Paule</hi> was married, whence had he a wife, at <hi>Philippos?</hi> the which Citie it is not read that he entered into aboue twiſe, and where it is credible that he neuer abode two whole mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths. To conclude, there is nothing leſſe agréeyng to the matter, than to ſpeake here of a wife, no nor of any woman (in my iudgement) it is probable, notwithſtanding I leaue it to the readers iudgement. The worde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whych <hi>Paule</hi> here vſeth, is in helping wiſe to apprehende &amp; embrace the ſame thing, <hi>Whoſe names are in the booke of life.</hi> The booke of life is the catalogue of the iuſt which are predeſtinate vnto life, as in <hi>Moyſes. Exodus, 33.32.</hi> This catalogue the Lorde kéepeth with himſelfe. Therefore the booke is nothing els but his eternall counſell determined in his breſt. For that ſayth <hi>Ezechiell</hi> the writing of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael. cap. 13.9.</hi> In the like reſpect it is ſaid. <hi>Pſal. 69.29.</hi> Let them be wiped out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the liuing, and not be written among the righteous: that is let them not be accounted among the elect of GOD, whome he aſcrybeth to hys Church, and to the borders of his kingdome. If any wil obiect that <hi>Paule</hi> therfore doth raſhly, who challenge vnto himſelfe power to pronounce the ſecrets of God: I anſwere that after a ſort we may iudge by ſignes, whereby God doth make his election manifeſt: yet ſo much as our capacitie can beare. Therfore in whomſoeuer we ſée y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> notes of adoption to appeare, let vs in the meane time accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them for the ſonnes of God, vntill the bookes ſhal be opened, which ſhal altogither reueale al things. It belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth only vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to god to knowe nowe thoſe that are his, and at length to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate the ſhéepe from the goats. But it is our duty, charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to iudge al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſhéepe, that obediently ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7789:45"/> vnto their paſtor Chriſte, who gather them ſelues into his ſhéepefold, and there abide conſtantly. It is our dutie ſo much to eſtéeme the gifts of the holy ghoſt, which peculiarly he beſtoweth vpon his elect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be to vs as it were ſeales of his hidden election</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>4</hi>
                     </bibl> Reioyce in the Lord alwaie: againe I ſay reioyce.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>5</hi>
                     </bibl> Let your pacient minde be knowne to all men. The Lorde is at hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>6</hi>
                     </bibl> Bee carefull for nothing: but in all thinges let your requestes bee knowne vnto God in praier &amp; ſupplication with giuing of thankes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>7</hi>
                     </bibl> And the peace of God which paſſeth al vnderstanding, ſhall keepe your harts &amp; minds in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>8</hi>
                     </bibl> Furthermore Brethren, whatſoeuer things are true, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer things are graue, whatſoeuer things are iuſt, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer things are pure, whatſoeuer things are amiable, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer things are honeſt: if there be any vertue, &amp; if there bee any praiſe thinke on theſe things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>9</hi>
                     </bibl> Which yee haue both learned, and receyued, and hearde, &amp; ſeene in me, doe thoſe things, and the God of peace ſhall bee with you.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 <hi>Reioyce in the Lord.</hi>
                  </hi> This is an exhortation applied to the time. For becauſe the ſtate of the godly was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, euery where dangers imminent, it might ſo fall out, that they being ouercome with ſorrowe &amp; impatience, might faint. Therfore he biddeth them, howſoeuer their eſtate were hated and troubled, neuertheleſſe to reioyce in the Lorde: for then eſpecially the ſpirituall conſolations wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord doo recreate and chéere vs, muſte ſhewe forth their ſtrength, when the whole world doo prouoke vs to deſperation: but we muſt conſider by the circumſtance of the time, howe forcible this voice would haue béene from <hi>Paules</hi> mouth, who might be the eſpecial cauſe of their heauines. For if they be afraide of perſecutions, of bonds, of baniſhment, or of death: here the Apoſtle commeth forth, who amideſt his bonds, in the midſt of hoate perſecutions, and in feare of death, is not only ioyful
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7789:45"/> but alſo chéereth vp others. The ſum therefore is this, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall happen, yet the faithfull who haue God on theyr ſide, haue ſufficient matter to reioyce. The repetition ſerueth to the amplification, as if he ſhould ſay: let this be a ſtrong &amp; ſtedfaſt ground vnto you, to reioice in the Lord, and that not for a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but that your ioy may be continued in him. For truly in this it differeth from the ioy of the world, becauſe we haue experience that that is deceitful, momentanie and ſoone vaniſheth away, and Chriſt alſo doth pronounce it accurſed, <hi>Luke. 6.25.</hi> Therfore that is ioy fixed in God which is neuer taken from vs. <hi>5. <hi>Let your patient mind.</hi>
                  </hi> This may <hi>2</hi> waies bée expounded, either that he biddeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rather to loſe their right than that any ſhoulde complaine of their cruelty &amp; rigor. As if he had ſaide: let all men with whome you deale, perceceiue your equity and curteſie, that their knowledge may ſignifie their experience. Or elſe, that he exhorteth them to beare all things paciently, which latter ſenſe doth rather pleaſe me: for the Grecians alſo call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the moderation of the minde, when as we are not eaſily moued with iniuries, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are not eaſily troubled with aduerſitie, but we kéepe ſtil an equal condition, to which purpoſe <hi>Cicero</hi> hath ſaid, my mind is qui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>et, which taketh all things wel and equally. Such an equity, which is as it were the mother of of patience, <hi>Paule</hi> here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of the Philippians, and which might appeare vnto al men by ſhewing forth hir effects as occaſion requireth. It ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to agrée with the name of modeſty, becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> in this place doth not forbid them to waxe inſolent, but quietly to behaue themſelues in all their affaires, and to temperate themſelues in ſuſteinyng either iniuries or diſcommodities. <hi>The Lord is at hand</hi> Here is a <hi>Prolepſis</hi> whereby he preuenteth an obiection: for the ſenſe of the fleſh reclaimeth agaynſt the former ſentence: for ſince that by our gentlenes the deſire of the wicked waxe more inſolent, and the more readye they ſée vs to beare, the more bold they are to offer iniuries, wée are hardly brought in this patience to poſſeſſe our ſoules: ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vpon came theſe prouerbs. We muſt howle among wolues,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:7789:46"/> that we ſhall ſoone be deuoured of wolues, which haue beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues like ſhéepe. Therefore we conclude that the fiercenes of the wicked is with like violence to be beaten backe, leaſt that ſafely they triumph ouer vs. Againſte theſe cogitations <hi>Paule</hi> here oppoſeth the truſte in God his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. He anſwereth I ſay, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord is at hand, whoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhal ouercome their boldnes, and whoſe goodnes ſhal van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh their malice: him he promiſeth to be preſent with vs, if we obey his commandement. And who had not rather be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tected only by the hand of God, than to haue all the aid of the worlde in a readines? An excellent ſentence, wherby firſt we learne, that the cauſe of all impatience is the ignorance of the prouidence of God: hereof it come that we rage ſo quickly, &amp; for ſo light a cauſe, &amp; often alſo we diſpaire becauſe we know not that the Lorde hath care of vs. Contrariwiſe, this is an only remedie to pacifie our mindes, if knowing that we are neither ſubiect to the raſhnes of fortune, nor to the luſt of the wicked, but that we are gouerned by the fatherly care of god, we reſt altogither vpon his prouidence. To conclude, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer holdeth this, that god is preſent with him, he hath wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to reioyce without feare. Moreouer the Lord is ſaide to bée at hand, two maner of waies, either becauſe his iudgement is at hand, or elſe becauſe he is ready to ſuccour his ſeruants: in the which ſignification it is taken in this place, as alſo in the <hi>Pſal. 145.18.</hi> The Lord is néere vnto al them that cal vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him: the ſenſe therefore is, the condition of the godly ſhould be moſt miſerable, if the Lorde were farre off: but becauſe the Lord hath receiued them into his tuition, and by his power which is preſent euery where doth defend them: let them ſtay themſelues vpon this cogitation, that they be not diſmaied at the rage of the wicked. It is knowne and common that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes is here taken for impiety, which ſpringeth from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt of gods power or of his help. <hi>6. <hi>But in all things.</hi> Paule</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſinguler number, but the neuter gender therefore in <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is as much as in al your buſines: becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are of the feminine gender. In theſe wordes he exhorteth the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7789:46"/> Philippians as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth al the godly. <hi>Pſal. 55.23.</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter 1.</hi> epiſtle. <hi>5.7.</hi> that they ſhould caſt al their care vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord: for we are not made of iron, but we may be ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: but this is the comfort. Here is our eaſe to lay downe (or to ſpeake more properly) to empty out into gods boſome whatſoeuer gréeueth vs. Confidence bringeth quietnes vnto our minds, but ſo that we be exerciſed by praiers. Therefore ſo oft as we are aſſalted with any te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let vs fly ſtraight vnto praier, as vnto an holy ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctuary. He taketh praiers here for deſires or vowes. He woulde haue them opened vnto god through praier: as if the faithful ſhould poure out their harts before the Lord, when they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend themſelues &amp; al their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires vnto him. They ſéeme to be ſomwhat lifted vp, which look hither &amp; thither vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vain ſolace of the world: but there is one ſure hauen to reſt vpon, the Lord. <hi>With giuing of thanks.</hi> Becauſe many pray vnto God, amiſſe either chiding or mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring as though they had iuſt cauſe to accuſe him of, others if he doo not ſtraight way gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their requeſt, can abide no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay. Therfore <hi>Paule</hi> ioyneth thanksgiuing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> praiers, as if he ſhould ſay, we muſt ſo wiſh of god thoſe things which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for vs, that notwithſtanding we ſubmit our affections vnto his wil, &amp; that in praying we giue him thanks. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankfulnes wil worke this in vs, that the wil of god ſhall be the chief ſum of our deſires. <hi>7. <hi>And the peace of God.</hi>
                  </hi> Some turning the future tenſe into the optatiue moode, doo make a praier of this ſentence, but falſly: for it is a promiſe wherein he ſheweth the fruit of firme truſting in god, and of Inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If you doo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſaith: <hi>The peace of god ſhal keepe your minds and your harts.</hi> The ſcripture is wont to diuide the ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> according to the powers therof into <hi>2.</hi> parts: the mind and the hart: the mind ſignifie the vnderſtanding, and the hart the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections or wils: therfore theſe <hi>2</hi> words comprehend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ſoule, in this ſenſe, the peace of God ſhall kéepe you, that you fal not from god by euil cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or deſires. And he calleth it truly the peace of god, which depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the preſent ſight of things, neither doth it change according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the world, but is founded on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant &amp; immutable
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7789:47"/> word of God. And he ſaith truly, that it paſſeth al vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or ſenſe, becauſe there is nothing more contrarye vnto mans wit, than in greateſt diſpaire, neuertheleſſe to hope, in greateſt pouerty to behold wealth, in greateſt weakenes not to faint, finally, to promiſe that we ſhall want nothing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are deſtitute of all things. And that altogither is in the alone grace of god, the which is not known but by the word, and the inward earneſt of the ſpirit. <hi>8. <hi>Furthermore.</hi>
                  </hi> Generall exhortations follow, which appertaine vnto the whole lyfe. In the firſte place he commendeth trueth, whiche is nothyng elſe than the integritie of a good conſcience, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. In the ſecond place he commendeth grauity or holines (for the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifie both) the whiche vertue is placed in this, that we walke worthy of our vocation, frée from al pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane vncleanes. In the thirde place he commendeth iuſtice, which pertaineth vnto mutuall communication among men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we hurt no man, or defraud no man. In the fourth place he comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth purity, which ſignifieth chaſtitie throughout our whole life But all theſe things are not ſufficient vnto <hi>Paule,</hi> except we ſtudy to make our ſelues amiable vnto all men, as much as it is lawfull in the Lord, and that we haue regard of our good report: for ſo I interpret <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>If any praiſe</hi> for that which is praiſe worthy: for both in the manners of men, which are ſo corrupt, there is ſuch peruerſenes of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that oftentimes that thing is commended, which is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious: and it is not lawfull for chriſtians to ſéeke true praiſe among men, who are forbidden to reioyce any other where than in God only. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> doth not bid them ſéeke praiſe or commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their good déeds, nor to frame theyr life according to the iudgement of the people: but only to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy good works which deſerue praiſe, that the vngodly and the enimies of the goſpell, whiles they deride and diſpraiſe the chriſtians, yet they may be compelled to commend their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Moreouer the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is ſpoken of the Gréekes as Latines doe <hi>Cogitare</hi> for <hi>Meditari,</hi> that is to thinke for to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate. Meditation goeth before, and then the worke follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7789:47"/> 
                  <hi>9 <hi>Which ye haue learned, receyued, and heard.</hi>
                  </hi> By this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of words he ſignifieth, that he was diligent in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching theſe things, as if he ſhould ſay, this was my doctrine, this was my tradition, this was my ſpeach among you. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe, the hypocrites did vrge nothing but ceremonies. And it were a ſhamefull thing to forſake that holy inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which they had thoroughly learned, and wherewith they were almoſt endued. <hi>Ye haue ſeene in me.</hi> This is the chiefeſt thing in a preacher, that he ſpeake not only with his mouth, but with his life, and that he bring credite to his doctrine by his vertuous liuing. Therefore <hi>Paule</hi> worthily from thence procureth authoritie vnto his exhortation, becauſe he was no leſſe in his life than in his mouth a captaine and maiſter of vertues. <hi>And the God of peace.</hi> He had ſpoken of the peace of God, now he confirmeth it more expreſſely, when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth that God himſelfe the author of peace ſhall bée with them. For the preſence of God bringeth vnto vs all goodnes whatſoeuer, as if he ſhould ſay, they ſhall perceiue that God is preſent with them, who will turne all things to their good and proſperitie, ſo that they apply themſelues to godly and holy works.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>10</hi>
                     </bibl> I reioyced alſo in the Lord greatly, that now at the laſt your care for me ſpringeth afreſh, of whome alſo ye were mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but yee wanted opportunitie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>11</hi>
                     </bibl> I ſpeake not becauſe of want, for I haue learned in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtate I am, therewith to be content.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>12</hi>
                     </bibl> I knowe both to be humble, and I knowe to excell: euerie where and in all things I am instructed both to be full and to be hungrie, to abound and to ſuffer pouertie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>13</hi>
                     </bibl> I am able to doo all things in Chriſt who ſtrengthneth me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>14</hi>
                     </bibl> Notwithſtanding yee haue done well in communicating vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mine afflictions.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 <hi>I reioyced alſo.</hi>
                  </hi> Now he declareth the thankefulnes of his mind to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> that they ſhould not repent of their beneficence, as it is wont to come to paſſe, when wée thinke that our duties are contemned, or nothing eſtéemed.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:7789:48"/> They had ſent vnto him by <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> ſuccour in time of his neceſſitie, he teſtifieth that it was a benefite verie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto him, and he ſaith, that he reioiced, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh they were in a new readines to prouide for him, it is a metaphore taken from trées, whoſe ſap lieth cloſe hidden in the winter, and in the ſpring beginneth to flouriſhe, but ſtraightway adding a correction, he alſo doth temperate this ſaying, leaſt he ſhould ſéeme to accuſe their negligence of the former time, therefore he ſaith, that before they were alſo carefull of him, but the opportunitie of the time ſuffered not that he was ſooner reléeued by their liberalitie, ſo he layeth the fault vpon an vnfit time. I haue referred thys part <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto <hi>Paule,</hi> and that is the proper ſignification, and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to <hi>Paule</hi> his text. <hi>11. <hi>I ſpeake not becauſe of want.</hi>
                  </hi> A ſecond correction, whereby he preuenteth the ſuſpition of a baſe mind and brought lowe by aduerſitie: for he did report, that his conſtancie and moderation was knowne vnto the <hi>Philippians,</hi> vnto whome he was an example of good life, therefore he pronounceth that he was ſo chéered by their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie, that he could yet patiently endure want. Pouertie is héere referred to the affection, for he is neuer poore in mind who is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with his eſtate giuen him of God. He ſaith, <hi>In whatſoeuer ſtate I am.</hi> That is, whatſoeuer my eſtate is, it is ſufficient vnto me: wherefore? for the Saints knowe that they ſo pleaſe God, therefore they doo not meaſure ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by the plentie of things, but by the will of God, the which they eſtéeme aright, becauſe they are perſwaded that theyr affaires are gouerned by his will and prouidence. <hi>12 <hi>I know both to be humble.</hi>
                  </hi> Héere followeth a diſtributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that his mind is capable of either fortune: proſperitie is wont to puffe vp mens mindes aboue meaſure, and aduerſitie to caſt them downe, from both theſe vices he ſaith he is frée. I knowe, he ſaith, to be humble, that is, patiently to ſuffer humilitie, the Gréeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is héere twiſe put down, but in the firſt place it is taken for to excel, and in the ſecond, for to abound, that they might haue relation to their contraries. He that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7789:48"/> knoweth to vſe his preſent abundance of things ſoberly and temperately with thankeſgiuing, being ready to reſigne all whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall pleaſe the Lord, &amp; communicating with his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, according to the meaſure of his ability, &amp; is not puffed vp with pride, that man hath learned to excell and to be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: an excellent and rare vertue, and far greater than the enduring of pouertie. In learning this knowledge of <hi>Paule,</hi> let all be exerciſed that will be the diſciples of Chriſt, and in the meane ſeaſon let them ſo accuſtome themſelues to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure pouertie, that it be not hard &amp; gréeuous vnto them, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhall happen that they are depriued of their ſubſtance. <hi>13 <hi>I am able to do all things in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </hi> Becauſe he had boaſted of great matters, leaſt it ſhould be obiected vnto him as an argument of pride, or leaſt he ſhould giue others occaſion of fooliſh boaſting, he addeth, that he is indued with this ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth from Chriſt: I can, he ſaith, do all things, but in Chriſt, not by mine owne vertue, whereby we gather that Chriſt ſhall be no whit at all leſſe ſtrong &amp; forcible in vs, if being priuie to our owne weakenes, we ſtay our ſelues onely vpon hys vertue. Whereas he ſaith <hi>All things,</hi> he vnderſtandeth only thoſe things which belong to his vocation. <hi>14 <hi>Notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ye haue done well.</hi>
                  </hi> How wiſelie and warely he dealeth on either ſide, being circumſpect y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he incline not too much either to this or to that ſide. By ſetting out his conſtancie, magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally he would beware that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Philippians</hi> ſhould not thinke that he had fainted vnder his pouertie. Now he taketh héede, leaſt by ſpeaking boldly he might ſéeme to haue contemned their benefits, which were not only a point of diſcurteſie and contumacy, but euen of pride, &amp; together he addeth, that if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other of the ſeruants of Chriſt ſhould néede their helpe, that they ſhould not be ſlothfull to ſuccour them.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>15</hi>
                     </bibl> And yee Philippians knowe alſo, that in the beginning of the Goſpell, when I departed from Macedonia, no Church communicated with me concerning the matter of giuing and receiuing but yee only.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>16</hi>
                     </bibl> For when I was at Theſſalonica, yee ſent once and agayne that which was needefull for me.</p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:7789:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>17</hi>
                     </bibl> Not that I deſire a gift, but I deſire the fruite which may further your reckoning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>18</hi>
                     </bibl> Now I haue receiued all, and haue plentie: I was euen filled after that I had receyued of Epaphroditus that whiche came from you, an odor that ſmelleth ſweete, a ſacrifice acceptable and pleaſant to God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>19</hi>
                     </bibl> And my God ſhall fulfill whatſoeuer is wanting vnto you, according to his riches in glorie thorough Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>20</hi>
                     </bibl> Vnto God and father be praiſe for euermore, amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>21</hi>
                     </bibl> Salute all the Saints in Chriſt Ieſus: the brethren whiche are with me greete you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>22</hi>
                     </bibl> All the Saints ſalute you, and eſpecially they which are of Caeſars houſhold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>23</hi>
                     </bibl> The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with you all. Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>24</hi>
                     </bibl> Written from Rome by Epaphroditus.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15 <hi>Yee knowe.</hi>
                  </hi> I interprete that this was added to excuſe himſelfe, becauſe he had ſo oft receiued from them, for if the other Churches had performed their duties, he might haue ſéemed too couetous in taking, thus therefore by purging himſelfe, he commendeth them, and in commending them, he modeſtlie ſpareth others. We alſo muſt take héede by the example of <hi>Paule,</hi> leaſt the godly, whileſt they ſée vs too rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to take, doo worthely iudge vs vnſatiable: you, he ſaith, doo knowe, as if he ſhould ſay, it is not neceſſarie that I ſhould cite other witneſſes, for you your ſelues alſo knowe it, for it oft times come to paſſe that he which thinketh others to ceaſe in their dutie, is more liberall to ſuccour, ſo the one is ignorant of the others liberalitie. <hi>Concerning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and receiuing,</hi> he alludeth vnto the accompts of money, whereof there are two parts, the one of receipt, the other of expenſe, it is méete that theſe two by a mutuall compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be referred vnto an equalitie. Such an accompt was agréed vpon betwéene <hi>Paule</hi> and the Churches: when <hi>Paule</hi> miniſtred vnto them the Goſpell, there was a mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obligation that they ſhould miniſter vnto him things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for this life, as he ſaith <hi>1. Corin. 9, 11.</hi> If we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7789:49"/> vpon you ſpirituall things, what great thing is it if you giue vs againe carnall things: therefore if the other Churches had reléeued the neceſſitie of <hi>Paule,</hi> they had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him nothing of their owne, but paide their debt. For they muſt acknowledge that they had receiued the Goſpell of him, yet he denieth that they did not that, becauſe they ſpent nothing for his ſake. How ſhamefull an ingratitude is it, and full of how great vnworthineſſe, to neglect ſuch an Apoſtle, to whome they knew they were more bound, than they were able to pay? Againe, how great was the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the holy man, to beare their diſcurteſie ſo mildly and ſo méekely, that he doth not accuſe them with any bitter words. <hi>17 <hi>Not that I deſire a gift.</hi>
                  </hi> He reiecteth againe from himſelfe the ſiniſter opinion of an immoderate deſire, leaſt they ſhould thinke that it were a wrong inſinuation, as though they only ſhould doo the dutie of all, and he ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe their gentleneſſe, therefore he teſtifieth that he is more carefull for their commoditie, than for his owne. While I receiue any thing, he ſaith of you, ſo much groweth vnto you. For there are many names which yée beare in the tables of your accompts, that haue beſtowed any thing vpon me. The meaning of this word dependeth vpon that ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of exchange, or of paying of debts in the affaires of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. <hi>18 <hi>Now I haue receyued all and haue plentie.</hi>
                  </hi> He affirmeth more expreſſely that he hath ſo much as is ſufficient, and he adorneth their liberalitie with an excellent teſtimonie when he ſaith, that he aboundeth. Without doubt it was a meane ſumme which they had ſente, but with that mediocritie hée ſaith, he aboundeth vnto ſatietie: but that is a more excellent commendation of their reward which followeth, when he calleth it a ſacrifice acceptable vnto God, and an offering of a ſwéete ſmelling ſauour. For what better thing can wée wiſh for, then that our benefites ſhoulde be holy offerings, which God doth receiue at our hands, and with whoſe ſmell he is delighted? In like manner ſpeaketh Chriſt, Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yée haue done vnto one of the leaſt of theſe in my name,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7789:50"/> ye haue done it vnto me. <hi>Matth. 25, 40.</hi> But the metaphore of ſacrifices addeth much moment, whereby we are taught that that ſame dutie of loue which God commaundeth, is not only beſtowed vpon men, but a ſpirituall and holy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is performed, euen to God himſelfe, as it is ſaide in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebr. 13, 16.</hi> with ſuch ſacrifices God is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: wo woorth our ſlothfulneſſe, that when God doth ſo gently inuite vs vnto the honor of this prieſthoode, and doth put the ſacrifice into our hands: we neither ſacrifice vnto him, and thoſe things which were appointed for holy offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, we doo not only conſume them on prophane vſes, but wickedly waſte them on moſt filthy corruptions. For the aulters wherevpon the ſacrifices of our wealth ought to be laide, are the poore and the ſeruants of Chriſt, but they being neglected, ſome ſpend it on all kind of riot, ſome on glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, ſome on lecherie, and ſome on building faire houſes. <hi>19. <hi>And my God ſhall fulfill.</hi>
                  </hi> Some reade, <hi>I beſeech my God to fulfill</hi> in the optatiue moode, which although I reiect not, yet I more allowe the other reading. He calleth God by name his God, becauſe he doth impute and acknowledge that it is done to himſelfe whatſoeuer is performed vnto hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, therefore they had truely ſowed in the fielde of the Lord, from whence they ſhould hope for a certaine and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull harueſt: neither doth he only promiſe them a reward in the life to come, but alſo concerning the vſe of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life, as if he ſhould ſay, thinke not that touching youre ſubſtance you are impoueriſhed, for God whome I ſerue, will abundantly ſupply vnto you whatſoeuer ſhall be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie. This part <hi>In glorie,</hi> muſt be reſolued into the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe gloriouſlie, magnifically, or famouſlie, but he addeth, <hi>Thorough Chriſt,</hi> in whoſe name euerie thing is acceptable vnto God which we do. <hi>20 <hi>Vnto God and our father.</hi>
                  </hi> It may be a generall thankeſgiuing, wherewith he concludeth the Epiſtle, or it may ſpecially be referred vnto the next ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, concerning the liberalitie beſtowed on <hi>Paule,</hi> for that the <hi>Philippians</hi> ſuccoured him, he ought ſo to thanke them,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7789:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> that he ſhould notwithſtanding acknowledge that he was reléeued by the mercie of God. <hi>22 <hi>All the Saints ſalute you.</hi>
                  </hi> In his ſalutations he firſt nameth his fellowes, afterwarde all the Saints in generall, that is, the whole Churche of <hi>Rome,</hi> but eſpecially them of <hi>Nero</hi> his houſhold, the which is worthy to be marked, for it is not a common token of God his mercy, that the Goſpell had pearced into that bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit of all wickedneſſe and vngodlineſſe: and it is ſo much the more maruelous, as the example is rare, that holineſſe ſhould raigne in Princes courts: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as ſome haue coniectured, that <hi>Seneca</hi> is here noted among the reſt, it hath no ſhew of truth, for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did he euer at any time by any token proue himſelfe a Chriſtian neyther was he of <hi>Caeſar</hi> his houſe, but a Senator and a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped in the printing.</head>
            <p>Fol. <hi>7.</hi> line <hi>22.</hi> for they ſhould be thankefull, reade we ſhould be thankefull.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>10.</hi> line <hi>19.</hi> for in our bowels, reade in the bowels.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>14.</hi> line <hi>20.</hi> for <hi>in Castrum Praetorum,</hi> reade in Latine <hi>Praetorium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>eod.</hi> lin <hi>11.</hi> for to proue they lie, reade to proue their lie.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>37.</hi> lin <hi>36.</hi> for great exaltation, reade ſo great exaltation.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>39.</hi> line. <hi>11.</hi> for in the ſenſe, reade in this ſenſe.</p>
            <p>Fo. <hi>44.</hi> li. <hi>13.</hi> for they gather meate, reade they gather merite.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>47.</hi> line <hi>21.</hi> for that which ſhall be glorious, reade that that ſhall be glorious.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>53.</hi> line. <hi>9.</hi> for becauſe we ſaid, reade yet we ſaid becauſe.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>60.</hi> line. <hi>36.</hi> for head, reade heart.</p>
            <p>Fol. <hi>64.</hi> line. <hi>20.</hi> for liberall, reade literall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7789:51"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
